<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessednes of the Virgin Marie the mother of our Lord Iesvs Christ.</title>
            <author>Shaw, John, 1559-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22391</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838969</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838969</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3362</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3362)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1219:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessednes of the Virgin Marie the mother of our Lord Iesvs Christ.</title>
                  <author>Shaw, John, 1559-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Field dwelling in Great Woodstreete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Shaw.</note>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Page 57 misnumbered 23.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The blessednes of Marie.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed lacks title page and other preliminary pages. Title and imprint from Bodleian Library copy spliced (beginning-page 25) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Blessed Virgin, Saint --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3362:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3362:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BLESSEDNES OF <hi>MARIE</hi> the Mother of IESVS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE 1.28.45.48.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Bleſſed art thou among women.</l>
               <l>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued.</l>
               <l>All generations ſhall call me bleſſed.</l>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field</figDesc>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by RICHARD FIELD dwelling in Great Woodſtreete. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3362:73"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3362:73"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL AND WORTHY LADIE, Ladie DOROTHY ZOVCH, the <hi>vertuous wife of Sir</hi> EDWARD ZOVCH <hi>Knight, at Oking:</hi> IOHN SHAW deſireth increaſe of all true comfort here, and hereafter euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Scripture of truth, wherein the myſteries of Religion are treaſured vp, hath three (amongſt others) not a litle more eminent, moſt worthie of our daylie and holieſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. They are by ſome called,<note place="margin">Bernardus in Vigilia Natalis.</note> 
               <hi>The wonders of wonders,</hi> &amp; are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt admirable, and ſurpaſſing
<pb facs="tcp:3362:74"/> comfortable for vſe, manifeſted by the Higheſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. Heid feldius.</note> for the ſure bleſſedneſſe of all Gods children, without which, all men had periſhed eternally. Not to ſpeake of the bleſſed Trinitie, the greateſt of all myſteries; the three here meant, are three <hi>Vnions,</hi> or <hi>Couplings</hi> in one, of things in themſelues moſt different.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the <hi>Vnion of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head to Manhood,</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> whereby he is God and man, <hi>Immanuel, God with vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the Coupling of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood</hi> and <hi>Virginitie</hi> in one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the bleſſed <hi>Marie,</hi> whereby her Sonne is called <hi>The Sonne of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third is, the begetting of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing-faith,</hi> in the <hi>ſoule</hi> of ſinfull man, whereby a ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh a childe of God, an heire of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>The firſt, and third of theſe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, are ioyntlie declared by <hi>Paul,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Great is the myſterie of
<pb facs="tcp:3362:74"/> godlineſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> God was manifeſted in the fleſh. — Beleeued on in the world.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was foretold by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Behold a Virgine ſhall conceiue and beare a Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are comfortable ſecrets, which none fruitfully know but the Lords he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, that are taught by his Spirit. Theſe manifeſt how God is neare vnto vs, and dwelleth with vs, and in vs, as in his holy Tabernacle. Theſe are the appointed means of our ſaluation and bleſſednes. Theſe myſteries ſo high, and holy, muſt be ſought into by humble and earneſt prayer, with much reuerence of heart, by reading, hearing, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue meditation; we muſt beleeue them, and reioyce greatly in the ſound and laſting conſolation they bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>When man by his ſinne was wofully fallen from God, and the bleſſedneſſe wherein he was ſet, and by his Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<pb facs="tcp:3362:75"/> had caſt himſelfe and his poſteritie into the ſtate of damnation: then, euen then did God manifeſt his vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loue in reſtoring him againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fauour of his <hi>Creator,</hi> and to the hope of a greater bliſſe then that which he had loſt. It was agreeable to the Lords holyneſſe, for manifeſting his mercy and iuſtice, that as man made the fault, ſo man ſhould make the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends. But man alone could not do it, (the <hi>Creator</hi> onely could repaire the creature.) God therefore becometh man, that ſo he might throughly do it. And he was manifeſted in the fleſh, (not for a ſmall time, as he appeared to the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches,) but the ſecond Perſon in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>The WORD, euen the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father, was made fleſh, and dwelt among vs, full of grace and truth.</hi> That man might be made partaker of the diuine nature, &amp; enioy eternall peace with God: <hi>The Captaine of our ſaluation tooke not on him
<pb facs="tcp:3362:75"/> the nature of Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>but he to tooke on him the ſeed of Abraham; in all things it behoued him to be made like his brethren, that he might be a mercifull and faithfull High-prieſt, in things pertaining to God, to make Reconciliation for the ſinnes of the people.</hi> This is the first, high, glorious, and comfortable myſterie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond craueth of vs like holy admiration and firme faith. Will God dwell in a Tabernacle? in a Temple? or as Salomon ſaith:<note place="margin">1. King. 8.27.</note> 
               <hi>Wil God indeed dwell on the earth?</hi> will he that made the heauens, take fleſh of the wombe of a Virgine? haue her indeed to be his mother, and yet ſhe continue a pure and vndefiled maide? Yes aſſuredly, &amp; it is a wonder without all example, and a miraculous worke of him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.4.</note> 
               <hi>that alone worketh wonders.</hi> Motherhood and virginitie meete in Marie, the most bleſſed of women, &amp; in her alone. And hath correſpondencie, to that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb facs="tcp:3362:76"/> Creation in the beginning, where <hi>Eue,</hi> the mother of all liuing, was miraculouſly made out of the ſide of man alone: ſo of the wombe of a woman alone, was borne the holy Meſſiah, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, for the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Couenant of grace, which God made with man. <hi>The womans ſeede ſhall bruiſe the ſerpents head.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> This is the ſecond ſecret, and high myſterie of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>The third wonder is, that faith and mans ſoule ſo meet, that man who is a ſinfull ſonne of <hi>Adam;</hi> by faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh a child of God, according as it is written:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note> — <hi>Ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we may take vp <hi>Dauids</hi> words, and ſay:<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.3.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, what is man, that thou takeſt knowledge of him, or the ſonne of man, that thou makeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of him?</hi> The difficultie of ſound beleeuing in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Sauiour of his elect, and the wonderfull mercy
<pb facs="tcp:3362:76"/> of God in that rare grace, will better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if we call to minde, how that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in Paradiſe, man beleeued not God, (when he ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt die the death:</hi>) and did beleeue the diuel,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>(Ye ſhall not ſurely die.)</hi> Now that man is fallen from integrity, and captiued in Originall and Actuall ſin, to beleeue a promiſe of eternall life, that God will make him an heire of heauen, for Ieſus ſake, is aboue all humane learning, ſenſe and reaſon. And this hope and confidence is onely in that litle flocke, where Gods Spirit doth powerfully worke it. How few beleeue, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth:<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.1.</note> —<hi>Who hath beleeued our report? and to whom is the arme of the Lord reuealed?</hi> How great a work of God, faith is, <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth: — <hi>Who beleeue according to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his mighty power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.19</note> 
               <hi>which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead.</hi> Certainlie as there was a darkneſſe in all Egypt,
<pb facs="tcp:3362:77"/> 
               <hi>that</hi> might be felt:<note place="margin">Exod. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>but all the children of Iſrael had light in their dwellings:</hi> Euen ſo all the choſen Iſrael of God now, haue <hi>Chriſt the light of the world dwelling in their hearts by faith.</hi> But the whole world of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and vnbeleeuers, loue darkneſſe and abide in it for euermore.</p>
            <p>Hereupon it followeth, that Iewes, Turkes, Pagans, Vnbeleeuers, and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, who haue no communion by faith with the Sonne of God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the fleſh, abide vnder the curſe and wrath of the Almighty. But the choſen litle flocke, to whom the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Christs kingdome are known, who ſoundly, and with all their heart, beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God, conceiued by the holy Ghost, borne of the virgine <hi>Mary;</hi> that he the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> is their king, prieſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and by his obedience vnto death, hath wrought their full Redemption, and made their reconciliation with
<pb facs="tcp:3362:77"/> God: theſe through faith in his bloud, haue Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed to them for the attaining of ſaluation; theſe haue a ioy glorious and vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; theſe cleaue to God in true holines; and in the end, for this their Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſake, receiue a crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and the bleſſedneſſe promiſed that laſteth euermore.</p>
            <p>This litle Treatiſe will ſo far lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, &amp; vnfold theſe three profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, as may giue occaſion to the well-minded readers, to make further ſearch into ſo high, holy, and neceſſarie do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, as are primary pillars of true Religion.</p>
            <p>And now, worthie <hi>Madame,</hi> in that I commend vnto you, my poore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours contained in this litle booke, it is out of a good deſire, to further you in the best things, to procure you ſome litle helpe, to get greater increaſe of the chiefe bleſſings; to caſt in my myte by writing alſo, to adde that way ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb facs="tcp:3362:78"/> to your ſpirituall treaſure, of <hi>knowledge, holineſſe,</hi> and <hi>comfort,</hi> as one deſirous to be thankfull to God for his manifold mercis to you, in that ſince your coming among vs, you make it daily euident, that you haue a hearty loue to true Religion; and take much comfort in the Miniſtery, and publike worſhip of God eſtabliſhed: as alſo that by your good example, &amp; blameleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſation, you grace your holy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, going before many, in many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duties. Aſſure your ſelfe, your careful labouring to grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Ieſus Christ, will giue you an heauen vpon earth, and ſhall be your crowne in the day of the Lord: when all thoſe that ſuffer their hearts to be ſtolen away from God and godlineſſe, by exceſſiue cares or pleaſures of this world, ſhall haue their ſorrowes come vpon them like armed men, and their end ſhall be fully miſerable. Mind you it well, I pray
<pb facs="tcp:3362:78"/> you;<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Though a ſinner do euill an hundred times, and his daies be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, yet ſurely I know, that it ſhall be well with them that feare God, which feare before him. But it ſhall not be well with the wicked, neither ſhall he prolong his dayes, which are as a ſhadow, becauſe he feareth not before God.</hi> Earneſtly, &amp; conſtantly ſeeke after thoſe laſting ioyes, where is mirth without all mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, life without vexation; eternall happineſſe, by a bleſſed communion with the eternall God, who wil be all in all to them that loue him.</p>
            <p>Paſſe ouer no day, wherein you call not to minde, the many, ſweete, free bleſſings of the almighty, beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; but by them prouoke your ſelfe to offer to him, the heartiest ſacrifice of thankſgiuing that you can attaine to, acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, faithful, feruent prayers, for increaſe of his beſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to you and yours; that your happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3362:79"/> begun here, may be continued e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly.<note place="margin">Act. 20.32.</note> And now I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you vp, and to giue you an inheritance, among all them which are ſanctified.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.23.</note> And the very God of peace ſanctifie you throughout, and I pray God, your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and bodie, be preſerued blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, vnto the coming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Be thou faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee a crowne of life.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Reuelation <hi>2.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3362:1"/>
            <head>THE BLESSEDNES OF THE VIRGIN <hi>MARIE,</hi> the Mother of our Lord IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE 1.28.45.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Bleſſed art thou among women.</l>
               <l>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holie Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.28</note> writing the miraculous Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that is, his wonderfull <hi>Conception</hi> and Birth: deſcribeth the meſſenger that mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted theſe glad tidings, to be the Angell <hi>Gabriel;</hi> the woman that ſhould be mother to Ieſus, by name <hi>Marie,</hi> by condition a Virgin, affian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3362:2"/> to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Dauid;</hi> the place of their dwelling Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, a towne of Galile in the land of Iudaea; the time, in the dayes of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar:</hi> the child to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and borne of her, by name <hi>Ieſus;</hi> by office and dignitie, a King ouer the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> for euer; by nature the Sonne of the eternall God; by ſpeciall fauour, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his humane nature, the ſonne of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> conceiued in her wombe, the holie Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vpon her, and the power of the Higheſt ouerſhadowing her, &amp; ſhe thrice by holy Oracle, aſſured, that ſhe is exceedingly bleſſed.</p>
            <p>The Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from the royall Kings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> found grace and fauour with God, was freely beloued of him, precious and honorable in his ſight; had great honour put vpon her, was exceedingly bleſſed by Gods ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3362:2"/> loue to her, euen bleſſed aboue all women.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Maries bleſſedneſſe is twofold.</head>
               <p>The firſt is ſingular and proper to her ſelfe, a prerogatiue granted to her alone, and neuer to any other creature: euen to be the <hi>Mother of Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the Sauiour of all the Elect, the mother of <hi>Emmanuel, God-with-vs,</hi> euen God manifeſted in the fleſh. Thus ſaith <hi>Gabriel</hi> from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <hi>Bleſſed art thou among women,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.28</note> thus ſaith holy <hi>Elizabeth</hi> on earth: <hi>Bleſſed art thou among women,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">42.</note> 
                  <hi>and bleſſed is the fruite of thy wombe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that hauing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained like precious faith with the <hi>Saints in the common ſaluation,</hi> ſhe with them, abiding in the truth of Religion, did beleeue, and waite for the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and her owne ſaluation by him; as in her holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3362:3"/> ſhe acknowledgeth:<note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſoule reioyceth in God my Sauiour.</hi> She had alſo a peculiar proper holy faith, in a peculiar promiſe which was made to her alone,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.12.3.</note> which was, <hi>That the bleſſed ſeede, in whom all the families of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, ſhould be her ſeede;</hi> that the Sonne of God would become her <hi>ſonne,</hi> and be borne of her wombe; and of theſe, holy <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the mother of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.45.</note> ſaith: <hi>Bleſſed is ſhee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Bleſſed art thou among all women.</head>
               <p>The ſingular bleſſedneſſe and rare prerogatiue, that <hi>Marie</hi> at once is a maide and a mother, beareth a ſonne, and is ſtill a Virgine; is both a daughter of God, and a mother of the Sonne of God; is a wonder of wonders, a ſtrange miracle, glorious and comfortable: not fruitfully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3362:3"/> of any but of them that are taught of God, who maketh knowne the myſteries of his kingdome to babes and little ones, according to the good pleaſure of his wil: and this part of the ſauing truth, he writeth in our hearts by his Spirit, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of it is in his word, thus recorded by the Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſixt moneth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.26.</note> 
                  <hi>the Angell Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel was ſent from God, vnto a Citie of Galile named Nazareth, to a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine eſpouſed to a man, whoſe name was Ioſeph, of the houſe of Dauid, and the Virgins name was Marie, and the Angell came in vnto her and ſaid; Haile, thou that art highly fauoured, the Lord is with thee: Bleſſed art thou among women. Thou haſt found fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with God, and behold, thou ſhalt conceiue in thy wombe, and bring forth a ſonne, and call his name Ieſus. He ſhall be great, and ſhall be called the Sonne of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3362:4"/> the Higheſt, and the Lord God ſhall giue vnto him the throne of his father Dauid, and he ſhall reigne ouer the houſe of Iacob for euer: and of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there ſhall be no end. Then ſaid Marie to the Angell, How ſhall this be, ſeeing I know not a man? And the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell anſwered and ſaid vnto her: The holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and the power of the Higheſt ſhall ouerſhadow thee: therefore alſo that holy thing, which ſhall be borne of thee, ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sonne of God. And behold thy coſin Elizabeth, ſhe alſo hath conceiued a ſonne in her old age, and this is the ſixt moneth with her who was called barren: For with God nothing ſhall be vnpoſſible. And Mary ſaid, Behold the handmaide of the Lord, be it vnto mee according to thy word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This moſt ioyfull wonder, that God will dwell with man, be man, be borne of a Virgine, is the firſt ſweete Propheſie, and gracious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3362:4"/> that God made to man in Paradiſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The womans ſeede ſhall bruiſe the ſerpents head:</hi> that is, Ieſus Chriſt, the ſeede and ſonne of the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> ſhall deſtroy the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell (that ſpake by the ſerpent) and his kingdome, and worke mans full deliuerance, and eternall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. This worke of God, ſo ſtrange and glorious, is the fulfilling of the propheſie of <hi>Iſaiah:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 7.14.</note> 
                  <hi>A Virgine ſhall conceiue, and beare a ſonne, and ſhe ſhall call his name Emmanuel;</hi> for in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time appointed by the Lord, <hi>The word was made fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, full of grace and truth:</hi> euen he who is <hi>holy, harmeleſſe, vndefiled,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 7.26.</note> 
                  <hi>ſeparate from ſinners, and made higher then the heauens.</hi> The holy God, that of old declared himſelfe from aboue the <hi>Mercie-ſeate</hi> in the Tabernacle,<note place="margin">Exod. 25.22. Heb. 1.2.</note> hath <hi>in theſe laſt dayes ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne, whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed heire of all things, by whom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3362:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo he made the worlds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This rare miracle, ſo wonderfull in the eyes of men &amp; Angels, which had that due acclamation;<note place="margin">Luk. 11.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the wombe that bare thee, and the paps that gaue thee ſucke;</hi> will more clearly appeare in the excellencie of it, if we compare it with the conceptions and birthes that the worthieſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men euer had, or with this of the bleſſed Virgine <hi>Marie.</hi> And to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the ancienteſt:</p>
               <p>EVA, the mother of vs all, when ſhe had conceiued, and borne a ſon, thankfully acknowledged Gods loue therein,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.1.</note> ſaying: <hi>I haue obtained a man by the Lord.</hi> Yet had ſhe no comfort of him,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.12</note> 
                  <hi>For he was of that wicked one, and ſlue his brother:</hi> but <hi>Maries</hi> ioy was ſound, full, and laſting; for ſhe did not onely obtaine a man of the Lord,<note place="margin">Act. 4.27.5.31.</note> 
                  <hi>but a man which is the Lord. The holy childe Ieſus. A Prince and Sauiour,</hi> euen <hi>the Lord of glorie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.8.</note> of whom not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3362:5"/> onely <hi>Elizabeth</hi> a good woman, and <hi>Gabriel</hi> an holy Angell, gaue ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable a teſtimonie: but euen God the Father from heauen, thus witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>in whom I am well pleaſed; heare him. Peter</hi> alſo auoucheth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.17</note> that <hi>He recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from God the Father, honour and glorie, when there came ſuch a voice to him, from the excellent glorie, This is my beloued Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>SARA, when ſhe was ninetie yeares old, was made ioyfull with this comfortable promiſe of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie: <hi>I will bleſſe her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 21.6.</note> 
                  <hi>and will alſo giue thee a ſonne of her, yea I will bleſſe her, and ſhe ſhall be the mother of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Kings alſo of people ſhall come of her.</hi> If <hi>Sara</hi> praiſe the Lord, ſaying: <hi>God hath made me to reioyce, all that heare, will reioyce with me: I haue borne to Abraham, a ſonne in his old age:</hi> much more may bleſſed <hi>Marie</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3362:6"/> ſay, <hi>God hath made me to reioyce,</hi> and <hi>from henceforth all generations ſhall call me bleſſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.48.</note> 
                  <hi>for he that is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath done for me great things, and holy is his Name.</hi> For I haue borne a ſonne,<note place="margin">Reu. 17.14</note> who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. <hi>The Prince of peace, the increaſe of whoſe gouernment and peace ſhall haue none end;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall ſit vpon the throne of Dauid, and vpon his kingdome to order it, and to establiſh it with iudgement and with iuſtice, from henceforth and for euer. A King ſhall reigne and proſper,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 23.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute iudgement and iuſtice in the earth; in his dayes Iudah ſhall be ſaued, and Iſrael ſhall dwell ſafely, and this is the name whereby they ſhall call him: the Lord our righteouſneſſe. This King ſhall reigne ouer the Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.12. Mat. 1.21. Reu. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and in him ſhall the Gentiles truſt. He ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinnes, and make all his redeemed, Kings and Prieſts vnto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3362:6"/>
               <p>HANNA, the godly wiſe of <hi>Elka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> was barren a long time; but when with earneſt prayer and teares ſhe had begged and obtained a ſonne of God, euen <hi>Samuel,</hi> and giuen him to the Lord all the dayes of his life, and had brought him when he was weaned, to Silo, that he might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Lord, and there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide for euer: ſhe praiſed God chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, <hi>and reioyced in his ſaluation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and that the barren had borne.</hi> Now if this holy Prophetiſſe gaue praiſes to God, for ſuch a worthy and gracious ſonne,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.20.</note> euen <hi>faithfull Samuel the Lords Prophet:</hi> much more had the bleſſed Virgine cauſe to magnifie the Lord, that made her mother of ſuch a ſonne, as is both the greateſt <hi>Prophet,</hi> and holieſt <hi>Prieſt,</hi> that euer was.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Prophet</hi> thus <hi>Moſes</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and <hi>Peter</hi> reporteth:<note place="margin">Act. 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe vp vnto
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3362:7"/> you, of your brethren like to me; him ſhall ye heare in all things, whatſoeuer he ſhall ſay vnto you: and it ſhall come to paſſe, that euery ſoule which will not heare that Prophet, ſhall be deſtroyed from among the people.</hi> He is the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.46.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſpake as neuer man ſpake:</hi> He that maketh knowne to vs, <hi>all things that he heard of his Father:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.15.</note> He that taught with authoritie of a Lawgiuer;<note place="margin">Mat. 7.29.</note> that with his gracious words giueth his Spirit,<note place="margin">Act. 10.44.</note> opening &amp; powerfully bowing the heart; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all his elect wiſe <hi>to ſaluation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>through faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This holieſt PRIEST was after the <hi>order of Melchiſedech,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>had compaſſion on the ignorant, and them that are out of the way. He in the daies of his fleſh, offered vp prayers and ſupplications, with ſtrong crying and teares, and was heard; — and became author of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that obey him.</hi> This moſt holy,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> high PRIEST, <hi>is perfectly able
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3362:7"/> to</hi> SAVE <hi>them that come to God by him, ſeeing he euer liueth.</hi> He is our REDEEMER,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>In whom we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through his bloud.</hi> He is our RIGHTEOVSNES:<note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>By the obedience of one many ſhall be made righteous.</hi> He is our RECONCILER:<note place="margin">10.</note> 
                  <hi>When we were enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne.</hi> He is the MEDIATOR <hi>of the new Couenant:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.24 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>entred into heauen, now to appeare in the preſence of God for vs.</hi> He is our ADVOCATE <hi>with the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and the propitiation for our ſinnes; he is at the right hand of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.33</note> 
                  <hi>and maketh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>BATHSHEBA, the mother of King <hi>Salomon,</hi> had great cauſe to bleſſe God, that gaue her a ſonne, ſo great, &amp; ſo good; who gaue ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor vnto his mother, as is reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred in the holy word,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 2.19</note> that <hi>The King roſe vp to meete her, and ſate downe on his Throne, and he cauſed a ſeate to be ſet
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3362:8"/> for the Kings mother, and ſhe ſate at his right hand:</hi> But bleſſed <hi>Marie,</hi> had a greater and better ſonne, euen him,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.11.</note> 
                  <hi>to whom all knees bow;</hi> euen him, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> This <hi>ſonne</hi> did highly honour his mother. Firſt in his <hi>ſubiection</hi> to her, for it is written, that <hi>he was obedient to her.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.51.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his holy care for her, and that in his extreme anguiſh on the croſſe.<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>There ſtoode by the croſſe of Ieſus his mother, and when he ſaw her and the Diſciple ſtanding by, whom he loued: he ſaith vnto his mother, Woman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy Sonne; then ſaith he to the Diſciple: Behold thy mother; and from that houre, that Diſciple tooke her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne home.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas conformitie to <hi>Gods</hi> image, and ſound holineſſe, is a great part of true bleſſedneſſe; this moſt godly Virgine ſhewed forth ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and rare vertues: for being at a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3362:8"/> Mariage with Chriſt at Cana in Galile: her <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion</hi> was made euident, when ſhe ſpake to her ſonne, <hi>They haue no wine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 2.3.</note> her <hi>meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that kept ſilence when Chriſt rebuked her; alſo her <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting &amp; perſwading to that which is the ſumme of our duty, moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to that voice of God from heauen, <hi>Heare him:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 17.5.</note> when ſhe exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſaying:<note place="margin">Iohn 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuor he ſaith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, do it.</hi> She ſuffered much affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for Chriſt, (and ſo was parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of that dignity of the Saints,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.29.</note> that both beleeue in Chriſt and ſuffer for his ſake:) both when ſhe liued as an exile with him in Egypt;<note place="margin">Mat. 2.14.</note> as alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Simeons</hi> prophecie was fulfilled in his bitter paſſion:<note place="margin">Luk. 2.35.</note> 
                  <hi>A ſword ſhall paſſe through thy ſoule.</hi> She perſiſted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in the profeſſion of Religion, and continued in, and with the holy Church and aſſembly of the Saints, in all true holineſſe: as it is ſaid,—
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3362:9"/> 
                  <hi>They all continued with one accord in prayer and ſupplication,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Marie the mother of Ieſus, and with his brethren.</hi> Thus it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euidently, that ſhe was a bleſſed mother, of a moſt bleſſed Sonne: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen bleſſed among, and aboue all women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="use_and_fruit">
               <head>The firſt vſe and fruite for Confutation.</head>
               <p>We knowing and beleeuing the wonderfull conception and birth of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, do controll the madneſſe, and confute the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſies of all that impugne the two diſtinct natures of that one perſon <hi>Immanuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 7.14.</note> (who is the Sonne of God eternally, and the ſonne of <hi>Marie,</hi> borne of her wombe in the fulneſſe of time, decreed before the world was made;) or that any way derogate from his Propheticall, Prieſtly, or kingly offices, by which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3362:9"/> he wrought the ſaluation of his Church.</p>
               <p>This doctrine ſoundly grounded on the word of God, refuteth the Iewes of this age, that yet waite for MESSIAH, who is already come in humilitie to redeeme his Saints, and will the ſecond time come in glorie,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.28.</note> to crowne them, and confound his foes;<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8</note> and will then <hi>repay vengeance to all them that know not God, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea moreouer, As <hi>euery ſpirit that confeſſeth, that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God: ſo euerie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that confeſſeth not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>that Ieſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God; and this is that ſpirit of Antichriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ye haue heard, that it ſhould come, and euen now already is in the world.</hi> There is no other true <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> but <hi>Ieſus</hi> Chriſt the Sonne of the virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> whoſe bleſſed mouth hath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3362:10"/> ſaid:<note place="margin">Iohn 8.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Except ye beleeue that I am he, ye ſhall die in your ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="use_and_fruit">
               <head>The ſecond vſe and fruite for confirmation.</head>
               <p>Our holy faith and ſoundeſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, are confirmed ſtrongly in the ancient gracious Couenant of God made in Paradiſe, often renewed to the Patriarches and Church of the Iewes, accompliſhed when God was manifeſted in the fleſh, &amp; dwelt among vs, when Chriſt was borne of the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> as it is written: <hi>In the fulneſſe of time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>God ſent forth his Sonne, made of a woman, made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, to redeeme them that were vnder the Law, that we might receiue the adoption of Sonnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.10.</note> 
                  <hi>With the heart we do beleeue, and with the mouth we confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt, conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> is the <hi>Immanuel; (God with-vs,)</hi> foretold by the Prophet <hi>Iſaias; made
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3362:10"/> like vnto vs in all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 4.15. Ioh 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>yet without ſinne.</hi> Euen <hi>that Lambe of God, which taketh away the ſinne of the world.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen he by whom all effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.14.</note> 
                  <hi>receiue the promiſe of eternall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</hi> For be it, that we all were conceiued in ſinne, and borne in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and corrupted in all the parts of our ſoules and bodies: yet the Conception, Birth &amp; whole nature of Chriſt our Sauiour, was fully ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, by being vnited to his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and imputed to vs, ſo that the holineſſe of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> is a robe to couer all our ſinfulneſſe, and whereby we ſhall ſtand moſt gloriouſly in Gods ſight, in the great day of the Lord. For as <hi>Eſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſter 5.3.</note> aduanced from low eſtate to be a great <hi>Queene,</hi> had not this dignity put vpon her for her ſelfe alone, but alſo for the comfort of all her kinred, euen all the Iewes: ſo that the glorious <hi>Meſſiah</hi> was borne of the bleſſed Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3362:11"/> was not her bleſſedneſſe alone, but redounded to the ioy, honour and ſaluation of all that beleeue in him,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.11.</note> be they Iewes or Gentiles.</p>
               <p>This high, holy, and comfortable myſterie, why God would become man, to worke mans ſaluation, though it be greater then can be well expreſſed: yet let vs endeuour ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meringly to vtter what we haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therein.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.8.</note> And as <hi>Iotham</hi> (in the booke of Iudges) vſed a parable to declare his mind more plainly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The trees went forth on a time, to annoint a king ouer them,</hi> &amp; ſo forth: So we deſire without offence to vſe a <hi>Dialogue</hi> or diſputation, to ſee if this myſterie ſo profound may be better vnderſtood, or leaue a deeper impreſſion of ſo holy learning. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> (and in him all his poſteritie) by diſobedience had ſinned againſt God, before he ſhould receiue the doome of his iuſt damnation, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3362:11"/> ſtood vp to pleade.</p>
               <p>IVSTICE tooke the firſt place, and with much vehemencie alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that the righteouſneſſe of God required, that vnleſſe there were a ful ſatisfaction made by man for mans tranſgreſſion, man muſt neceſſarily die, and that eternally, for his ſinne; and that God could not be iuſt, if any of his debts ſhould paſſe vnſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Infinite Iuſtice is wronged, therefore muſt man endure infinite torments. The moſt holy and iuſt God hath ſpoken:<note place="margin">Gen. 2 17.</note> 
                  <hi>In the day thou eateſt of the tree of the knowledge of good and euill, thou ſhalt die the death:</hi> Againe he hath ſaid:<note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſed is euery one that continueth not in all things, which are written in the booke of the Law, to do them.</hi> Yea and againe: <hi>The ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 18.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>TRVTH likewiſe ſtood vp and ſaid: My ſentence muſt needs be, to ſecond &amp; make good all that <hi>Iuſtice</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3362:12"/> hath ſpoken: for what God ſaith is true, all his words are as the faithfull witneſſes in heauen, and <hi>He will be knowne by executing of iudgement:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.16.</note> Be ye well aſſured,<note place="margin">Num. 23.19.</note> 
                  <hi>God is not as man, that he ſhould lie: hath he ſaid and ſhall he not do it? and hath he ſpoken, and ſhall he not accompliſh it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>MERCIE then put forth her voice, Giue me place alſo to ſtand for, and to witneſſe, what is noted in the Scripture of truth. For though I may in no part derogate from <hi>Iuſtice</hi> or <hi>Truth,</hi> whoſe greatneſſe I know and reuerence: yet know ye alſo, that <hi>Mercie</hi> will loſe neither her right or preheminence, but will take firſt place of you both: for it is allotted by the word vnto me. It is firſt ſaid, <hi>Gracious and</hi> (then) <hi>Righteous is the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 25.8.</note> Yea let it be engrauen in pillars of marble, and written with letters of gold, and in the hearts of all the holy ones:<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.8.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is gracious and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3362:12"/> mercifull, ſlow to anger, and of great mercie.</hi> Yea I will auouch it confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, that where there is one title of Gods <hi>Iuſtice, (He maketh not the wicked innocent;)</hi> there are ſeauen ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of his <hi>Mercie: Iehouah, Iehouah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34.6</note> 
                  <hi>ſtrong, mercifull, and gracious, ſlow to anger, abounding in goodneſſe and truth, reſeruing mercie for thouſands, forgiuing iniquitie, and tranſgreſſion, and ſinne.</hi> If <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſay, man ſhall die: <hi>Mercie</hi> ſaith, <hi>he ſhall liue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 16.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>PEACE then very mildly tooke part with <hi>Mercie,</hi> and ſaid: Siſter <hi>Truth,</hi> I blame thee not for ſpeaking on <hi>Iustice</hi> ſide, for we haue learned that God is true in his <hi>threatnings,</hi> none will herein gainſay thee: but ſpeake vnpartially, (as I well know thou wilt when it cometh to thy turne to ſpeake againe:) is not God alſo as true in his holy Couenants, and all his ſweete promiſes? But without more vrging thee, I will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3362:13"/> ſpeake for vs both, and in the words of the holy Ghoſt. — <hi>As I haue ſworne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.9.</note> 
                  <hi>that the waters of Noah ſhould no more go ouer the earth, ſo haue I ſworne, that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee; for the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſhall depart, and the hils ſhall be remooued, but my kindneſſe ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of my peace be remooued, ſaith the Lord that hath mercie on thee.</hi> If rigor of Iuſtice ſhould take ſuch place, that man for his <hi>Sinne</hi> ſhould eternally periſh, then <hi>Mercie</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> ſhould be quite baniſhed out of the earth. But I know aſſuredly, <hi>That he will ſpeake peace vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and to his Saints. The Lord will bleſſe his people with peace.</hi> Yea vnto man,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> &amp; for man is giuen <hi>the Prince of peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WISDOME then (as beſt able to decide this controuerſie) tooke place and ſaid: All of you haue ſpoken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3362:13"/> well, and as beſeemeth you; for God will make his Name glorious, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting before men and Angels the holineſſe of his <hi>Iuſtice, Truth, Mercie</hi> and <hi>Peace. Mercie</hi> muſt be ſhewed, otherwiſe man cannot be ſaued; and yet God will not ſhew <hi>Mercie</hi> to violate or wrong his Iuſtice. There is a way found out by him whoſe name is <hi>Wonderfull</hi> and <hi>Counſeller,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> how to pleaſe you all, and to giue you full contentment, and to ſaue men from deſerued damnation.</p>
               <p>There is a law made by the moſt High, the <hi>Iuſt</hi> and <hi>Mercifull</hi> God, wherein it is thus enacted. — <hi>If thy brother be impoueriſhed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 23.47.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a ſtranger by thee, after he is ſold he may be bought out,</hi> ONE OF HIS BRETHREN <hi>may buy him out: — any of the</hi> KINRED <hi>of his fleſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his familie may</hi> REDEEME <hi>him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to the equity of this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3362:14"/> law, ſome ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> that is a <hi>Brother,</hi> muſt make the <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Attonement,</hi> who can pay all the forfets and debts of man, who can die, and yet ouercome death; die and be no debter to death, but meerely of loue, lay downe his life, to ſaue other from dying; who can perfectly fulfill the whole Law, and purchaſe the Creators fauour, and an eternall inheritance. For God by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t requiring of man, ſound, full, and perfect obedience; without a perfect and complete obedience, will not make man righteous: and threatning a curſe, &amp; ſetting downe the penaltie, will admit of no ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, but by the ſuffering of that curſe denounced by God himſelfe. Now ſuch a ſuretie, and man of worth that can thus ſuffer, and thus do, where ſhall he be found?</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Adam</hi> and all his ſonnes were ſilent, deiected, and heartleſſe;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3362:14"/> for no ſuch could be found on earth, man could do nothing to worke his recouerie, no more then a dead man can raiſe vp himſelfe out of his graue,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> 
                  <hi>being dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes;</hi> ſo that <hi>Deſperation</hi> was readie to arreſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and to take him from Gods gracious preſence for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: but the SONNE OF GOD came in due time to helpe at neede, and to ſaue that which was loſt, and he gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſpake; I will take fleſh of the wombe of a Virgine, I will become man, rather then man ſhall periſh, whom I created after mine owne image. He fell not altogether of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but by temtation of another; &amp; another that is more mighty ſhall raiſe him vp, and reſtore him fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fauour of his Creator. And this ſhall be accompliſhed, as <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> hath made it plaine vnto you, &amp; altogether according as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of me in the volume of Gods booke:</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3362:15"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note>
                  <hi>The iniquitie of all ſhall be laid on me, and I will make reconciliation, I will be wounded for mans tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the chaſtiſement of his peace ſhall light vpon me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>To finiſh tranſgreſſions, and to make an end of ſinnes, I will make my ſoule an offering, and be cut off from the land of the liuing; I will make my graue with the wicked,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 53.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and</hi> (yet) <hi>ſee my ſeede, and prolong my daies, and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in my hands. I will make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for tranſgreſſors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 9.24.</note> 
                  <hi>and bring in euerlaſting righteouſneſſe. This will I do,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 40.8.</note> 
                  <hi>for the Law of God is in my heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eternall Father being euer well pleaſed in his Sonne, agreed, (yea before determined,) that this ſoueraigne <hi>Remedie</hi> ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, before he pronounced the ſentence of iudgment: Yea he pligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Couenant of grace</hi> betweene him and man, (in few words, but containing in them the fulneſſe of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3362:15"/> true comfort and bleſſedneſſe,) <hi>The womans ſeede ſhall bruiſe the ſerpents head.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus was the great controuerſie decided, and the diſceptation ended. <hi>Mercy and truth met together,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> 
                  <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and peace kiſſed each other. Iuſtice</hi> was ſatisfied, <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> well pleaſed, <hi>Mercie</hi> triumphed, Sin was aboliſhed, Death deſtroyed, Hel vanquiſhed, Satan troden vnder foote, Man eternally ſaued, Heauen opened, Angels ioyfully ſung; <hi>Glorie be to God in the highest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and on earth peace, goodwill towards men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O that mans heart were rightly affected (to reioyce vnſpeakably, &amp; praiſe God vnceſſantly,) for this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious harmonie, where the wiſdome, power, mercie, iuſtice and truth of God meete in one, to worke mans reconciliation to God, and his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall bleſſedneſſe!<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.8.</note> 
                  <hi>O that the redeemed of the Lord, would praiſe the Lord for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3362:16"/> his goodneſſe, and for his wonderfull workes to the children of men!</hi> O what an incomprehenſible loue is it, that the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> 
                  <hi>who being in the forme of God, thought it no robberie to be equall with God, yet made himſelfe of no reputation, and tooke vpon him the forme of a ſeruant; and was made in the likeneſſe of man, &amp; being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and became obedient vnto death, euen the death of the croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the bleſſed <hi>Immanuel</hi> (that as <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12</note> ioyned heauen and earth together,) muſt be equall to God, to ſatisfie Gods iuſtice, and procure his loue to vs: he muſt be in the forme of a ſeruant, a man, a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a kinſman; <hi>Touched with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our infirmities, yet without ſinne.</hi> In which holy <hi>myſterie, Iob</hi> was well inſtructed, when ſo confidently he repoſed all his comfort in his kinſman,<note place="margin">Iob 19.25.</note> in his <hi>Redeemer: I know that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3362:16"/> my Redeemer</hi> (the word is <hi>Goali,</hi> my kinſman) <hi>liueth, and he ſhall ſtand at the latter day vpon the earth; &amp; though after my skin, wormes deſtroy this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God.</hi> Without this kinſman of our fleſh, and mighty holy <hi>Redeemer,</hi> there is no coming to God, but as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid: <hi>Except your brother be with you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 43.5.</note> 
                  <hi>ye ſhall not ſee my face.</hi> So high is Gods maieſtie, and ſo low is mans wretched eſtate, that to make an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and attonement betweene vs, we ſtood in neede of ſuch a <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> as muſt be both the Sonne of God, and of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Phyſitions tell vs, how the ſoule of man from heauen, and the body from earth,<note place="margin">Bright in Melanch. 9</note> are by the ſpirit of life brought to liue together in a maruellous concord and vnitie. The ſoule is meerely diuine, the body meerely a lumpe of earth: but that which maketh either to affect other,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3362:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3362:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3362:18"/> be as handfaſted, and comfortably to dwell together, is the ſpirit, though not ſo excellent as the ſoule; yet cometh it from the diuine influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of life; and not of it ſelfe earthy. So the golden claſp whereby God will be ioyned to man, dwell with him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> and in him, is the <hi>Word</hi> incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, equall to the Father and the holy Ghoſt touching his Godhead, but inferior to them touching his manhood. By him we haue acceſſe vnto God with boldneſſe, by him we haue right to the eternall inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, by him we haue comfort in our ſtrangeſt and ſtrongeſt tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It is written for our comfort, that <hi>He is not aſhamed to call vs bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.11.</note> ſaying; <hi>I will declare thy Name among my brethren. Ioſeph</hi> highly aduanced in Egypt,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.11.</note> did not onely preſerue all his brethren from periſhing in that great famine; but procured alſo for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (and that with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3362:18"/> the Kings good liking) that although (as ſhepheards) they were abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Egyptians, yet they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed <hi>Rameſes</hi> in <hi>Goſen,</hi> euen the beſt of the kingdome: So our tender hearted <hi>Ioſeph</hi> Chriſt Ieſus, our moſt louing brother, (fleſh of our fleſh) hath reconciled vs to God, and ſo preuailed for vs,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.32</note> 
                  <hi>That it is our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good pleaſure to giue vs the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Let euery true Chriſtian then be comforted with this free, full, and laſting loue of God towards vs in Chriſt, and returne the ſacrifice of daily, true, and heartie thankſgiuing, and ſay: <hi>Bleſſe the Lord O my ſoule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and forget not all his benefits, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth all thine iniquities, and healeth all thy diſeaſes; who redeemeth thy life from deſtruction, and crowneth thee with louing kindneſſe and tender mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THE SECOND DEGREE of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3362:19"/> bleſſedneſſe of the bleſſed Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> is ſet downe in theſe words: <hi>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.45.</note> 
                  <hi>for thoſe things ſhall be performed which were told her of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bleſſed <hi>Marie</hi> beleeued in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Sauiour promiſed, as all the holy ones of that age did, and in greater meaſure, and daily ſhewed forth the fruits thereof; Chriſt dwelt in her heart by faith before he was conceiued in her wombe. She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued moreouer, that <hi>He</hi> ſhould be the bleſſed fruit of <hi>her wombe,</hi> that the holy promiſed ſeede ſhould be her ſeede, that the Sauiour of all the elect ſhould be both her Sonne and her Sauiour. Her faith was holy, ſound, and ſtrong, when paſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all earthly thoughts that might haue moued to doubtfulneſſe, ſhe reſted firmly and faithfully on the Lords word and promiſe, with ſure aſſent and much certainty, ſaying:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3362:19"/> 
                  <hi>Be it vnto me according to thy word.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.38.</note> Whereas <hi>Zacharias</hi> (a man that walked in the ordinances of God without reproofe, hearing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from an Angell, that his aged wife ſhould beare a ſonne) doubted through ſome vnbeleefe,<note place="margin">Luke 1.20.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was made dumbe for a time, till Gods promiſe was fulfilled. Is it not a rare, excellent, and glorious faith, to beleeue that which neuer any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did beleeue? to haue ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, ſetled perſwaſion without wauering, and to ſeale that God is true, when the promiſe made ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth contrary to all ſenſe, reaſon, and experience? Looke we on the faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo often extolled in the Scriptures, and conſider if her faith was not as great, ſtedfaſt, holy, and excellent as his, if not more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, in that a woman beleeueth the Angell once aſſuring the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which he a man was often told,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3362:20"/> and that by the Lord himſelfe. It is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom 4.18</note> 
                  <hi>That againſt hope, he beleeued in hope, that he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the father of many nations, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that was ſpoken, So ſhall thy ſeede be: and being not weake in faith, he conſidered not his body now dead, when hee was about an hundred yeares old, neither yet the deadneſſe of Saraes wombe; he ſtaggered not at the promiſe of God through vnbeleefe, but was ſtrong in faith, giuing glorie to God, being fully perſwaded, that what he had promiſed he was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, and therefore was it imputed to him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> So holy <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> knowing her ſelfe to be a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, and by that ordinarie courſe of nature ſhe could not bring forth a child: yet minding there was a ſure promiſe, made by the God of truth, recorded by a holy Prophet, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by all the Iſrael of God: <hi>Behold a Virgine ſhall conceiue and beare a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 7.14.</note>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3362:20"/> 
                  <hi>ſonne, and ſhall call his name Immanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:</hi> And ſeeing now the God of her fathers, had ſpoken to her by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angell <hi>Gabriel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.30.</note> 
                  <hi>— Thou haſt found fauour with God, and behold thou ſhalt conceiue in thy wombe, and bring forth a ſonne, and ſhalt call his name Ieſus:</hi> She firmly beleeuing, <hi>that with God nothing is impoſſible,</hi> that all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God are moſt ſure, ſhe ſtrong and ſtedfaſt in her moſt holy faith, gaue glory to God, being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded that what he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, he was able to performe; made this ſweete anſwer.<note place="margin">Luk. 1.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the handmaide of the Lord, be it vnto me according to thy word.</hi> It followeth then, that as <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the faithfull, was accounted righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous by beleeuing: ſo likewiſe the faith of holy <hi>Marie</hi> was imputed to her for righteouſneſſe (and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for bleſſedneſſe) as it is ſaid: <hi>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3362:21"/>
               <p>If any hard of beleefe, take excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſay, <hi>Maries</hi> bleſſedneſſe is auouched onely by a woman: let ſuch remember, that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> that ſaid it, was both an holy woman, &amp; a Prophetiſſe, and the word of God ſpeaketh euidently of her:<note place="margin">Luke 1.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Elizabeth was filled with the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer if any ſay, we hold it for good, that ſound, true, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular beleeuing the promiſes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, giueth aſſurance of full bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe: but is <hi>Maries</hi> faith ſuch, in beleeuing ſhe ſhould beare a ſonne, yet remaine a Virgine ſtill?</p>
               <p>We deſire ſuch not to ſeuer things ſo nearely ioyned together, her faith of hauing a ſonne, and her faith in her ſonne; (who alſo is the Sonne of God bleſſed for euer.) For it is euident by the word, that ſhe both beleeued her own ſaluation by him the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> did; as alſo with a fuller light of knowledge,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3362:21"/> that the hope of Iſrael ſhould be her ſonne. By the one ſhe hath a prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, to be bleſſed aboue all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: by the other, a preeminencie amongſt all the Lords holy ones.</p>
               <p>By comparing Scriptures toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we ſhall ſee very clearly, that we ought not ſo to reſtraine the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe words, <hi>Bleſſed is ſhe that beleeued.</hi> We reade in Geneſis;<note place="margin">Gen. 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>The word of the Lord came to Abraham a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine—One ſhall come out of thine owne bowels, he ſhall be thy heire; looke now vp to heauen, and tell the ſtarres, if thou be able to number them, and he ſaid: So ſhall thy ſeede be, and Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham beleeued the Lord, and he accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that to him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> It is not to be gathered hence, that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was accounted righteous in beleeuing he ſhould haue a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full great poſteritie, like the number of the ſtarres for multitude; but he formerly beleeued this promiſe of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3362:22"/> the Almightie:<note place="margin">Gen. 12.3.</note> 
                  <hi>In thee ſhall all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the earth be bleſſed.</hi> Now the latter promiſe, Gen. 15. containeth in it the former, Geneſ. 12. and hath ouer and aboue it, a promiſe of the boundleſſe enlargement of the Church, which ſhould be bleſſed with him, by the promiſed ſeed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by him who is called <hi>Shilo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49.10 Iſa. 7.14. Dan. 9.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> and <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the holy Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> euen before the Angell came to her, ſoundly beleeued in the promiſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and that he ſhould be the ſonne of a Virgine, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaias</hi> had foretold: but after that <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi> the Lords meſſenger had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed more to her, ſhe beleeued that ſhe was that Virgine, to whom this dignitie and prerogatiue was freely giuen, to be the mother of the moſt holy <hi>Immanuel.</hi> So hauing the common faith of <hi>bleſſedneſſe</hi> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> &amp; this peculiar faith aboue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3362:22"/> 
                  <hi>Abraham,</hi> (for he ſaw Chriſt afarre off, but ſhe felt him in her wombe, firſt ſaw him manifeſted in the fleſh, heard his gracious words, enioyed him as her ſonne and Sauiour,) we may hold it as a manifeſt truth, that ſhe was before all in true and holy faith in the Sonne of the euerliuing God, hauing teſtimonie of her faith and bleſſedneſſe from the whole Church of God, as is prophecied— <hi>All generations ſhall call her bleſſed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.48.</note> and from the ſound and worthie fruits of ſauing faith, which are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the word. It is among the praiſes of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, by Chriſts owne mouth:<note place="margin">Ioh 8.56.</note> 
                  <hi>Your father Abraham reioyced to ſee my day, and he ſaw it, and was glad. Marie</hi> did not onely <hi>reioyce in God her Sauiour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>but alſo magnified the Lord,</hi> that is, with heart and voice praiſed and extolled the greatneſſe and goodneſſe of God to her and the whole Church. From
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3362:23"/> her faith flowed the glorifying of God, ioy and gladneſſe to her owne ſoule, and a comfortable reuiuing of the hearts of all the godly, by witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in her ſweete ſong the fulfilling of Gods promiſes <hi>for helping vp his ſeruant Iſrael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.54.</note> We conclude then, that the Virgine <hi>Marie</hi> was a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous woman, freely and fully beloued of God, a Maide and a Mother, a faithfull Iſraelite, a primarie Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, an holy prophetiſſe, a daughter of God by adoption, a Mother of the Sonne of God by ſpeciall fauor, bleſſed in bearing Chriſt, bleſſed in beleeuing in Chriſt, bleſſed by him on earth, bleſſed with him in heauen for euermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="use_and_fruit">
               <head>The firſt vſe and fruite</head>
               <p>Which wee muſt reape by kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and beleeuing, that <hi>Marie was bleſſed in beleeuing;</hi> is, that we be taught and ſtrengthened by her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3362:23"/> to ſeeke all our bleſſedneſſe out of our ſelues, in Ieſus Chriſt, as he is the <hi>Head</hi> of his body the Church,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.23.</note> and by him as he is our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Redeemer</hi> and <hi>Reconciler.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> And that this gift is giuen of God, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs by faith onely: For that faith and no other grace giueth vs right vnto,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.8.</note> and maketh vs owners of this bleſſedneſſe which is in Chriſt, (the proper act of this faith being to <hi>receiue</hi> Chriſt, and apply him to vs in particular.) So that we muſt be ſoundly inſtructed, and vnmoueably ſetled, in this high &amp; holy doctrine, of the excellency of faith, and the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of it, for receiuing <hi>Ieſus</hi> our Sauiour to be our owne, and in him to haue and enioy free, full, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Looke we carefully into the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpenſation of our bleſſedneſſe, and we ſhall find it both plainly and plentifully taught in the word of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3362:24"/> grace. Life is primarily in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from him in the Sonne, and that for as many as <hi>receiue</hi> him, — <hi>The Father hath life in himſelfe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>and he hath giuen to the Sonne to haue life in himſelfe,</hi> but not onely for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but for all that beleeue on him. — <hi>This is the record,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh 5.11</note> 
                  <hi>that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> TO VS <hi>eternall life, and this life is in his Sonne.</hi> Now if it be giuen to vs, we muſt receiue this life and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, and Chriſt the giuer to <hi>dwel in our hearts by faith.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> By it we haue a neare vnion with his perſon, as members of his body, whereof he is Head, giuing vs life, (as feeling and motion are from the head, to all the naturall bodie.) And communion with all his graces, to our full bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And that it is the proper act of faith alone, to RECEIVE, is thus taught. — <hi>The true Light came vnto his owne, and his owne receiued him not;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
                  <hi>but as many as</hi> RECEIVED <hi>him,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3362:24"/> to them gaue he power to become the ſonnes of God, euen to them that</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEEVE <hi>on his name. Paul</hi> thus ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.14.</note> — <hi>That the bleſſing of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham might come on the Gentiles, through Chriſt Ieſus, that we might</hi> RECEIVE <hi>the promiſe of the Spirit</hi> THROVGH FAITH. In the ſame ſence the word of <hi>laying hold on</hi> is vſed, expreſſing the nature and act of true faith, in this exhortation: <hi>Fight the good fight of</hi> FAITH,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.12.</note> 
                  <hi>lay hold of eternall life, whereto thou art called.</hi> Faith is not a diſpoſition to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or a beginning of other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which vnited together, might be meritorious of life and glorie; (as ſome haue greatly miſtaken it) but it is a <hi>receiuing</hi> apprehenſion, laying hold on, and applying of Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, for whom, and by whom, we are acceptable to God, and heires of bleſſedneſſe. Our iudgement and faith muſt be grounded on Gods
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3362:25"/> holy word, which is moſt plaine and cleare in this great myſterie. It is no where ſaid, thy faith hath begun ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in thee, (though indeed there is no true vertue, but which floweth from faith; but it is ſaid by the Lord himſelfe.<note place="margin">Luke 7.50.</note>— <hi>Thy faith hath ſaued thee;</hi> as alſo,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.24</note>— <hi>He that beleeueth, hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from death to life.</hi> And the holy Apoſtles, in like manner ſet forth the ſweete and comfortable fruites of faith.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.39</note>— <hi>We follow faith to the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſoule.</hi> In another place, he ſaith:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24</note> 
                  <hi>We are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the Redemption that is in Ieſus Chriſt, whom God hath ſet forth, to be a propitiation through faith in his bloud, to declare his righteouſnes for the remiſſion of ſinnes that are paſt, through the forbearance of God, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare at this time his righteouſneſſe, that he might be iuſt, and a iustifier of him which beleeueth in Ieſus.</hi> To this agreeth that in <hi>Peter:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Receiue the end
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3362:25"/> of your faith, euen the ſaluation of your ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus is the <hi>obiect</hi> of our faith, which aſſureth vs of our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, iuſtification and full bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe; and hath his ſeate partly in the vnderſtanding, partly in the heart. In the mind and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, faith is a ſure knowledge and apprehenſion, that Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne of the Virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Sonne of God, the long pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed bleſſed ſeed, the Sauiour of all his choſen; And in the heart, it is a true and ſure perſwaſion, (wrought alſo in vs by Gods ſpirit) a confident application, that I haue right to him as giuen to me: waiting for all my bleſſedneſſe through him, relying, and caſting my ſelfe wholly vpon him. So I put to my ſeale,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.33.</note> that God is true, iuſt, and gracious, infinitely good, that extendeth ſuch mercie to me, freely, for his beloued Sonnes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3362:26"/> ſake, neither dare I do that wrong to God and my ſelfe, as to miſtruſt and doubt of his gracious promiſes, <hi>He that ſhall beleeue and be baptized,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 16.16.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall be ſaued. Ye are of God in Chriſt Ieſus, who of God is made vnto vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30</note> 
                  <hi>wiſedome, and righteouſneſſe, and ſanctification, and redemption.</hi> Hauing Chriſt to be ours, in whom the fulneſſe of the Godhead dwelleth, we haue by him free pardon of all our ſinnes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, the imputation of Chriſts righteouſneſſe to be ours, by his free gift, redemption through his bloud, freedome from the curſe and rigor of the Law, from guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, bondage, and puniſhment of ſinne, from condemnation and hell torments. By him we haue Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Attonement, ſure, ſweet, and laſting peace with God, bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with confidence to come to the throne of grace; the ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, whereby as deare children
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3362:26"/> of God we call him our Father, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his preſence, deſiring to do his will; we haue proſperitie and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie ſanctified vnto vs, to further vs to grow vp to full holineſſe; we haue peace of conſcience, ſenſe of Gods loue, ioy in the holy Ghoſt, the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in vs, teaching, enlightning, guiding, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and comforting vs, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the image of God in vs, ſetting beauty vpon our ſoules, giuing grace to be fruitfull in holy deſires and meditations, in all good words and workes; ſtrength to perſeuere in the knowledge &amp; loue of the truth, and carefull practiſe of all pietie, to fight the Lords battels valiantly &amp; proſperouſly, to get Satan trampled vnder our feete, to triumph in Chriſt, and finally with him to bee partakers of glorie and eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection_and_doubt">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3362:27"/>
               <head>An obiection and doubt</head>
               <p>From theſe words of the Apoſtle, —<hi>Now abideth faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.13.</note> 
                  <hi>hope, charitie, theſe three, but the greateſt of theſe is charitie.</hi> If charitie be greateſt, (ſay ſome) how then doth faith iuſtifie, and aſſure euery beleeuer of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe? Let ſuch be put in mind, that although charitie in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects be greater then faith: yet is it not that grace which receiueth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and life, but the excellencie and greatneſſe of it is ſeene in other things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, charitie is greater then faith, in continuance of time, neuer falling away, neuer ceaſſing, but laſting euer more as may appeare in the words going before, from 8. verſe. Faith and hope bring vs to Chriſt, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, and with him, full bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, there will be no more vſe for them twaine. Like as a man got into his countrey, arriued where he will
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3362:27"/> euer abide, needeth no more a ſhip to paſſe ouer the ſeas. Faith &amp; hope end with time: Charitie ouer liueth all time. When faith and hope ceaſſe with the world, charitie then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to a fuller perfection.</p>
               <p>Secondly, charitie is greater in fruitfulneſſe, to do good to Gods people, (the proper worke of faith being to fetch comfort from Chriſt, and conuey it into our owne ſoule.) Faith caſteth her eyes on God, and all his gracious ſweete promiſes. Charitie looketh on men compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionatly, to helpe and comfort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; and euen this good fruite ſpringeth from faith, as an apple from middeſt of bloſſome that grew before it. Faith is the ancient and the true mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both of hope and charity, and <hi>worketh by loue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> All theſe three gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are excellent, but faith is firſt, &amp; hath preeminence, firſt in giuing all glorie to God, that in his loue he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3362:28"/> made a free Couenant of ſaluation, and that in his truth he performed the ſame. Secondly, it is greateſt by giuing to man hold and poſſeſſion of the promiſed mercies, ſo that by it as with a hand, he taketh hold on, receiueth and locketh faſt into his heart the Couenant of ſaluation, yea receiueth Chriſt to dwell in the heart,<note place="margin">Ier. 23.6.</note> 
                  <hi>who is the Lord our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> Faith is like to the root of a tree, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth ſucketh in nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to beget and continually to preſerue and nouriſh the life and fruitfulneſſe of it: but charitie is like the branches of the tree, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing receiued vitall ſap, do put forth their fruits in due ſeaſon, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their kind. Faith may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the <hi>Magnes</hi> or loadſtone that draweth iron to it, and keepeth it faſt: Charitie to <hi>Hematites,</hi> that putteth out a vertue to ſtay bleeding. Faith is a <hi>Receiuer:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>We through the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3362:28"/> ſpirit wait for the hope of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by faith.</hi> Charitie is a <hi>Giuer,</hi> for hauing much giuen and forgiuen by Chriſt, we loue much,<note place="margin">Luke 7.47.</note> and giue back a reflexe of our loue, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God, and ſundry fruits of hearty loue for his ſake, eſpecially to them that excell in vertue. As in the body the eye and eare, haue their ſeuerall powers and offices, the one to ſee, the other to heare: ſo in the ſoule haue faith and charitie. Faith clingeth faſt to Chriſt, to haue in him iuſtification from ſinne, and his imputed righteouſneſſe to be ours. Charitie ſheweth forth the meaſure of our ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to hallow Gods name, to make ſure our election and calling, and willing and doing good to the Saints that are on earth.</p>
               <p>And this may ſuffice for anſwer to the firſt doubt: but faſten we yet our eyes more fully on the beautie of faith, whoſe faireneſſe and worth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3362:29"/> we cannot ſufficiently admire. That one place which is in the third of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and may be called the ſumme of the Goſpell, openeth the treaſure of grace to our view, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of ſauing faith, in theſe words: <hi>God ſo loued the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his onely begotten Sonne, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beleeueth in him, ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but haue life euer lasting.</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we aright the true cauſes of our bleſſedneſſe; and how great a gift it is, and to whom it befalleth. The firſt mouing cauſe is the free loue of God, his rich grace, mercy &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The ſecond cauſe, is the Sonne of God giuen vnto vs, who alſo gaue himſelfe to be our ranſome, perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to ſaue them that come to God by him. The third is the meanes or inſtrumentall cauſe, which is faith or beleefe, the very hand and mouth of the ſoule, to receiue Ieſus Chriſt and all his riches to be ours. The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3362:29"/> fourth cauſe is the end, for which the Father gaue his Sonne; &amp; hath two branches, the one, remouing of euill deſerued, <hi>(That we ſhould not periſh:)</hi> the other, the bringing in of our bleſſedneſſe purchaſed, expreſſed in theſe words, <hi>(But haue euerlaſting life.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Law accuſing ſheweth vs our ſinnes, and Gods angry coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and iuſt wrath againſt vs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen eternall damnation; when ſinne and iniquities ſeparate betweene God and vs, then muſt we apply by faith to our fainting ſoules, this glad tidings vttered by Chriſt, &amp; the like, to keepe vs from deſpaire. True it is, that the wounds of ſinne are deadly; but it is true alſo, that the ſalue and remedies to heale and helpe, are very ſoueraigne, to euery one that is ſound in the faith, and layeth them to his ſoule,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.14.</note> as a man putteth on his garment to keepe him from the cold.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3362:30"/> As our ſinnes are deformities, that make the ſoule foule and vglie, we haue <hi>Chriſt purging them by himſelfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> As they keepe vs in bondage, we <hi>haue Chriſt redeeming vs with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet 1.19.</note> As they are euill deeds that cannot be vndone, we haue <hi>Chriſt couering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.</note> As they are debts greater then we can pay, we haue <hi>Chriſt forgiuing them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.7.</note> As they are offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces againſt God, making vs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of eternall death, we haue <hi>Chriſt not imputing our ſins vnto vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4 8.</note> As they are diſobedience againſt God and his law reuealed to vs from heauen, we haue <hi>Chriſt fulfilling the law for vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10 4.</note> Yea we haue from the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer failing fountaine of grace,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed to vs,</hi> by which we are accounted, and are righteous, as if we had wrought all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe our ſelues, euen as one friend ſetteth another free, fully paying his debts for him. As <hi>Caiphas</hi> (ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3362:30"/> by Gods ſpirit) well propheſied, <hi>That Ieſus ſhould die for that nation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.50.</note> ſaying, <hi>Ye know nothing at all, nor conſider, that it is expedient for vs that one man ſhould die for the people, and that the whole nation periſh not.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> very comfortably tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, deſcribing the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4 23.</note> 
                  <hi>— And it was not written for his ſake alone, that it was imputed to him, but for vs alſo, to whom it ſhall be imputed, if we beleeue on him that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp Ieſus our Lord from the dead.</hi> How cleare is it in the word, that as <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience made vs all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo the obedience of Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all true beleeuers righteous? the words of the holy Ghoſt are theſe: <hi>As by one mans diſobedience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.19.</note> 
                  <hi>many were made ſinners: So by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous.</hi> For like as our ſinnes were imputed to Chriſt, when he ſuffered for vs, <hi>and bare our ſinnes in his body on the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25.</note>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3362:31"/> 
                  <hi>tree:</hi> ſo his righteouſneſſe is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and reckoned to be our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, through Gods gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, moſt iuſt and wiſe diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. Which alſo to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> is thus ſet forth: <hi>Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for vs. — That the bleſſing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles, through Ieſus Chriſt, that we might receiue the promiſe of the Spirit through faith.</hi> And yet more plainly to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made him to be ſinne for vs, who knew no ſinne, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the bringing in of <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe,</hi> mentioned in the ſecond branch, called <hi>euerlaſting life:</hi> it is ſo great, ſo good, and glorious a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as no heart yet can ſufficiently conceiue of the worth &amp; excellency thereof, where he ſhall alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold God in his glorie, and be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3362:31"/> with his likeneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.15.</note> yea confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him, and partakers of a ful and endleſſe glorie. It is the bounty and kindneſſe of the Higheſt to all his choſen little ones,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.7.</note> — <hi>That we ſhould be iuſtified by his grace, and be made heires according to the hope of eternall life:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.15</note> that we be <hi>annexed heires with Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and poſſeſſe the pleaſures at Gods right hand for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let it be carefully obſerued, and well remembred, that while we ſo highly commend the <hi>ſauing-faith,</hi> that aſcribeth glorie to God, and bringeth ſuch comfort to mans <hi>ſoule,</hi> we arrogate nothing to our ſelues, as if it were in our owne power to beleeue; but we acknowledge it meerely to be the free gift of God, as we are taught,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> 
                  <hi>That Ieſus is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and finiſher of our faith.</hi> We may not ſay that it is attained by mans skill and induſtrie, but that it is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3362:32"/> gift to Gods elect, as the holy word teacheth vs:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.29.</note> — <hi>To you it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to beleeue in his Name.</hi> It is a work of God, neither common nor ſmall: — <hi>Ye beleeue according to his mightie power.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 1.19.</note> And when God by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of his word, and power of his Spirit, hath wrought it in vs; yet through our infirmitie, it is weake &amp; imperfect, ſuch as ſtandeth in need of daily increaſing and confirming; ſo as that the Apoſtles of Chriſt prayed,<note place="margin">Luk. 17.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord increaſe our faith.</hi> Euen where faith is in truth, and ſound, it is but as a beggers hand to receiue a Kings bounty; or if you would haue a gayer ſimilitude to expreſſe it, it is like the firie chariot that caried <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> vp to heauen: or like a gold ring that hath a pearle or rubie ſet into it, the worth of the ring not being from the gold, but from the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pearle in it. Excellencie of faith is in apprehending and applying to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3362:32"/> vs the moſt precious <hi>Obiect</hi> of it, that is, Chriſt Ieſus, and in him <hi>eternall life;</hi> which the word doth plainly ſay, <hi>is the gift of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note> giuen onely to <hi>beleeuers;</hi> yet not for the worthineſſe of their perſons, or faith, but meerly of Gods loue and free fauour, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances befall to men for whom they are prepared.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 9.7</note> As lame <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</hi> was ſet continually at the kings table, not for any worth in him (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo a deformed cripple) but onely for <hi>Ionathans</hi> ſake: ſo we find acceptance with God, but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe <hi>he hath loued vs in his beloued.</hi> So that both the bleſſing,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.6.</note> &amp; to be made capable of it, is his moſt free gift. We ſee that Kings ſuffer their Nobles to enioy much honor, and great prerogatiues, yet they will ſuffer no fauourite to weare their crowne: So the Lord out of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and moſt rich grace, bequeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to vs in his holy Teſtament, the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3362:33"/> legacie of <hi>eternall life,</hi> and putteth faith into our hearts to ſeale the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof vnto vs; yet the honor (for the exceeding gift) he reſerueth to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.25.</note> and <hi>will giue it none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> We are all equally vnder the curſe; but when God calleth out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly by his word, and inwardly by his Spirit, giuing to vs faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <hi>in Chriſt our righteouſneſſe,</hi> our hearts are much comforted, and we greatly reioyce in the Lord. <hi>He that ſpared not his owne Sonne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.32</note> 
                  <hi>but deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him vp for vs all, how ſhall he not with him alſo freely giue vs all things? Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that iuſtifieth, who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, who is euen at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for vs.</hi> If the Sonne of God obey the Law for vs, die for vs, make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for vs; why ſhould we doubt of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3362:33"/> bleſſednes by him, ſeeing he caſteth off none, but ſuch as caſt him off through their vnbeleefe?<note place="margin">Heb. 3.18.</note> — <hi>To them that beleeued not, he ſware they ſhould not enter into his reſt.</hi> Dare man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his life that is ſo precious vnto him, to a ſhip made by the skill of man, in it to paſſe ouer the wide &amp; ſtormie ſeas: and ſhall we not boldly commend the whole ſafegard of our ſoules and bodies, to the Sonne of the euerliuing God, that laid downe his life for the ſauing of vs? Dare <hi>Benhadad</hi> put his life into the hands of his enemy, vpon this ground, that he had <hi>heard that the Kings of Iſrael were mercifull:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Kin. 20.31</note> and ſhall not we that are profeſſed Chriſtians, and deſire to be accounted for the children of the Higheſt, confidently, fully, and ioyfully reſigne our ſelues to Ieſus Chriſt, to claime the mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made vnto ſinners? eſpecially ſeeing he is at peace with vs, is our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3362:34"/> peacemaker, and taught vs that <hi>he came to ſaue ſinners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15 Gal. 3.26.</note> 
                  <hi>and that he hath made vs the children of God by faith in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.47.</note> 
                  <hi>with a Verily, verily I ſay vnto you, he that beleeueth on me, hath euerlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among all the ſeuen nations of the Cananites that for their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations were deſtroyed, the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites onely were wiſe, and eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped deſerued deſtruction;<note place="margin">Ioſ. 9.13.</note> for they ſought, and obtained peace with the Iſraelites: and yet had nothing to pleade for themſelues why they ſhould be ſpared, but put themſelues vpon their mercie, pretending that they came from a very far countrie, ſhewing their old garments, old ſhoes, old bottels, &amp; mouldie bread. So of all the people on the face of the earth, they onely will be found wiſe and happy, that diſtruſting their owne works, (done before grace as altogether ſinfull:) and thoſe done
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3362:34"/> after grace receiued, (as very faulty for not right vſing of them,) wholly deſpaire in themſelues, relie vpon, truſt to, and caſt themſelues fully on the rich mercy of God, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merits of Ieſus Chriſt; and firmly beleeue, that <hi>it is a true ſaying,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and worthie of all men to be beleeued, that Ieſus Chriſt came to ſaue ſinners.</hi> As <hi>Ionas</hi> was willingly caſt into the ſea,<note place="margin">Ionas 1.12.</note> to ſtay the raging of it, that all in the ſhip with him might not periſh, and they vpon his ſuffering, enioyed a calme and deſired ſafetie: ſo Chriſt Ieſus to appeaſe the wrath &amp; curſe that would haue fallen on vs, <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> and <hi>gaue himſelfe for vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to God for a ſweete ſmelling ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour;</hi> by it Gods iuſtice is ſatisfied, his wrath appeaſed, and all beleeuers reconciled. As he that was guiltie of manſlaughter, though he could make no ſatisfaction for the bloud he had ſhed, yet if he ſought to the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3362:35"/> appointed citie of refuge, by Gods mercifull diſpenſation and pardon, he was ſet free;<note place="margin">Num. 35.28.</note> (but it was) <hi>at the death of the High-prieſt:</hi> So we that can pleade nothing for our ſelues, being guiltie of many and great ſins, (euery one whereof deſerueth Gods curſe and damnation;) yet if we be truly humbled for them, ſeeke vnto Chriſt and beleeue,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.19</note> 
                  <hi>We haue boldneſſe to enter into the Holieſt by the bloud of Ieſus:</hi> and are commanded that <hi>we draw not backe vnto perdition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.39</note> 
                  <hi>but be of them that beleeue to the ſauing of the ſoule.</hi> For albeit our ſinnes are as bonds, death as a tormentor, hell an eternall priſon, the diuell as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant to arreſt, and as a iaylor there to keepe vs, becauſe we are indebted ten thouſand talents to the great King, (who will haue the debt payd) and we are vtterly vnable: yet one comfort,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.36.</note> (and but one) is left vs. <hi>If the Sonne make you free, ye ſhall be free
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3362:35"/> indeed.</hi> Now he hath freed the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as our High-prieſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.22.</note> and as our ſuretie paying our debts to God for vs. <hi>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſinnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18</note> 
                  <hi>the iuſt for the vniuſt, that he might bring vs to God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.14</note> Yea <hi>hath blotted out the handwriting that was againſt vs;</hi> and <hi>is a iuſtifier of him which beleeueth in Ieſus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.26</note> And like as <hi>Abraham</hi> with a ſtrong hand reſcued <hi>Lot</hi> his kinſman,<note place="margin">Gen. 14.16</note> when he was vnder the captiuitie of his enemies: after the like manner, Ieſus our King and kinſman,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.15</note> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Satan, ſpoyled principalities and powers, and deliuered vs out of his clawes. For when the Iudge and the Law are ſatisfied, what hath the Iay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor any more to moleſt the priſoner? Yea ſuch is Chriſts louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to all vnfeined repenting ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that beleeue, &amp; with the whole heart ſeeke to him,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> that <hi>He redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them from all iniquitie,</hi> &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>doth purifie them to himſelfe a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3362:36"/> peculiar people zealous of good works.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection_and_doubt">
               <head>A ſecond obiection and doubt.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.21.</note>
                  <hi>Was not Abraham our father iuſtified by workes when he had offered Iſaac his ſonne vpon the altar?</hi> Out of theſe words of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> ſome gather, that to be freed from ſin, &amp; ſo to obtaine bleſſedneſſe, <hi>(for bleſſed is the man to whom God imputeth none iniquitie;)</hi> is for the merit and worthineſſe of good workes. To which we anſwer, that not onely the words, but the true meaning of them is diligently to be pondred, leſt we ſhould thinke one Scripture to be contrary to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which cannot be. Gather we then the true ſenſe of them from the word it ſelfe; for as no man can ſee the Sunne that ſhineth, but by the light of the Sunne: ſo neither at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine we to the right vnderſtanding of the word, but by the other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as this may clearely be vnfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3362:36"/> by the words of S. <hi>Iames</hi> going before. For he well knowing, that many who by their profeſſion were Chriſtians, but in their conuerſation Libertines and Epicures, ſuch as made ſhew of <hi>Religion,</hi> but denied the power of it; ſpeakers of the word of God, but not doers of his will, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch as turned the grace of God into wantonneſſe: laboureth to ſet before them the danger thereof, and how they deceiued themſelues, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not vnderſtanding, or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the nature of true faith; &amp; he maketh it plaine to them, that they had no true faith, and by this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that they had not ſuch workes as neceſſarily proceed from a right faith. (Reaſoning as our Lord Ieſus Chriſt did:<note place="margin">Iohn 8.39.</note> 
                  <hi>If ye were Abrahams children, ye would do the workes of Abraham; but ye go about to kill me that tell you the truth, this did not Abraham.</hi>) Aſſuring them, that
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3362:37"/> 
                  <hi>faith if it haue no workes, is dead in it ſelf.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Wilt thou know O vaine man, that faith without workes is dead?</hi> For as where there is no heate, there is no fire: ſo where there is no good fruit, there is no true faith. But where faith is, there workes follow, and flow from it; as <hi>Abraham,</hi> by a rare and readie obedience, in a ſeruice ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature, and in appearance alſo to the great promiſe made vnto him, did make it manifeſt, what true truſt and ſtedfaſtneſſe of faith he had in the Lords holy promiſes. <hi>By faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.17</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham when he was tried, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp Iſaac, and he that had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the promiſes offered vp his onely begotten ſonne, of whom it was ſaid: In Iſaac ſhall thy ſeed be called.</hi> God gaue teſtimonie of theſe fruites of faith, when he ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 22.12</note> 
                  <hi>Lay not thy hand on the child, for now I know thou feareſt God; ſeeing thou hast not withheld thy ſonne, thy onely ſonne, from me.</hi> On
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3362:37"/> the other ſide, an hypocriticall and dead faith,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19</note> is like the fig tree with faire leaues, but hath no fruite on it; or if it haue a fruite, all we reade of, is compared to the faith of diuels; &amp; the fruite, feare and trembling: — <hi>Thou beleeueſt there is one God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>thou doeſt well: the diuels alſo beleeue, and tremble.</hi> But true faith hath with it, ioy and gladneſſe:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Though ye ſee him not, yet do you beleeue, and reioyce with ioy vnſpeakable and glorious.</hi> The manner of ſpeech which the holy Ghoſt vſeth, muſt be carefully obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if we will not fall into hereſies. What a dangerous noueltie of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is it to ſay, holy works done in faith are ſatisfactory, and meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of eternall life? whereas the word of God onely ſaith,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> — <hi>That they obtaine witneſſe of righteouſneſſe.</hi> As we reade, <hi>By faith Abel offered vnto God a more excellent ſacrifice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen Cain, by which he obtained wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3362:38"/> that he was righteous.</hi> As faith that is effectuall and fruitfull, giueth glorie to God for his goodneſſe and true performance of all his holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, in their appointed time: ſo the works that ſpring out of it, beare <hi>witneſſe</hi> to our ſelues and others, that we are not fruitleſſe trees, which are neare the curſe, but planted by the waters ſide, that bring forth fruit in due ſeaſon, whereby God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, our hearts comforted, and the faithfull praiſe God for vs. But on the contrary, ſuch as haue a bare knowledge, &amp; aſſent vnto the truth, or preſumptuous perſwaſion, not rightly grounded; ſuch as beleeue there is a God, but beleeue not in God (hauing no aſſurance he is their God) their gaines in the end is to be deceiued of their hope, and to be put in feare, horror, and trembling. Yea the <hi>fearefull and vnbeleeuing— ſhall haue their part in the lake which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.8.</note>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:3362:38"/> 
                  <hi>burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi> If any will yet perſiſt to preſſe the words of <hi>Iames,</hi> we vrge his words for our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, who ſaith:<note place="margin">Iam. 2.23.</note> — <hi>The Scripture was fulfilled, which ſaith: Abraham beleeued God, and it was imputed vnto him for righteouſneſſe, and he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the friend of God.</hi> But to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iames,</hi> vnderſtand, that <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh how <hi>Abraham</hi> was iuſtified <hi>declaratiuely,</hi> but <hi>Paul actiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> or <hi>effectually;</hi> which diſtinction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth both from the words, &amp; hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ſubiect in queſtion. If we would compare Geneſ. 15.6. with Geneſ. 22.19. and <hi>Iames</hi> 2.18, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> was approued for righteous, when he beleeued Gods promiſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen before <hi>Iſaac</hi> was borne; ſo it is as plaine as can be ſpoken,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.6.</note> — <hi>He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued in the Lord, and he accounted it to him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> But Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſheweth how he <hi>declared it,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3362:39"/> and made it manifeſt in worke and deed,</hi> by a rare obedience to God, —<hi>When he offered Iſaac his ſonne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the altar.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 2.21.</note> His faith ſo reſted on Gods promiſe, that although <hi>Iſaac</hi> were killed, and burnt to aſhes, — <hi>Yet God was able to raiſe him vp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.19</note> 
                  <hi>euen from the dead: from whence alſo he receiued him in a figure.</hi> All that are taught of God know, that <hi>faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by loue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> that it cannot be idle or fruitleſſe,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>God hauing created vs anew vnto good workes, which he hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that we ſhould walke in.</hi> Though they go not before iuſtification, yet do they follow it: where the Lord forgiueth ſinne, he alſo giueth a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to reſiſt ſinne, to hate and ſhun it, with a ſound deſire to practiſe ſuch holineſſe as through Chriſt is pleaſing to God. Though ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant people ſay, We are iuſtified for our good workes: yet the holy Ghoſt ſaith otherwiſe, namely, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3362:39"/> 
                  <hi>We are iuſtified freely by his grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>through the Redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Euen that <hi>grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath made vs accepted in his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, in whom we haue redemption through his bloud, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, according to the riches of his grace.</hi> Euen that grace, which is Gods eternall free bounty, and loue to vs, in electing, calling, adopting, and iuſtifying vs in Chriſt, who is <hi>the Lord our righteouſneſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 23.6.</note> not that infuſed grace, which is but as a drop, and fruit of the other, conſiſting in the renouation of the new man, which being but in part, (for they that haue greateſt meaſure,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.16</note> do what they would not, and leaue vndone what they would do,) is not able to ſtand before the Tribunall ſeate of iuſtice, which exacteth entire &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute obedience,<note place="margin">Deut. 27.26.</note> 
                  <hi>accurſing euery one that confirmeth not all the words of the Law to do them:</hi> Which moued <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:3362:40"/> to powre out this deſire of his ſoule:<note place="margin">Pſal. 143.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant, for in thy ſight ſhall none that liueth, be iuſtified.</hi> And <hi>Paul,</hi> who as touching the righteouſnes which is by the Law was vnrebukeable, yet <hi>counted all things loſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and did iudge them as dung, that he might win Chriſt, and might be found in him,</hi> that is, <hi>not hauing his owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, euen the righteouſneſſe which is of God through faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection_and_doubt">
               <head>A third obiection and doubt.</head>
               <p>It is ſaid of the godly profeſſors in Sardis, that had not defiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.4.</note> that they <hi>ſhall walke with me in white, for they are worthie:</hi> there is then (ſay ſome) a worthineſſe in our faith or works, or both together, by which we merit our bleſſedneſſe. That we may not miſtake this place,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3362:40"/> (ſeeing <hi>no propheſie of the Scripture is of any priuate interpretation:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.20.</note>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre it with <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35. <hi>They that ſhall be accounted worthy to obtaine that world, and the reſurrection from the dead:</hi> and that in 2. Theſſal. 1.5. <hi>That ye may be accounted worthy of the kingdome of God, for which ye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer:</hi> And we ſhall perceiue that theſe are worthy by acceptation in mercy, worthy by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed, not by holineſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent: the reward of going clothed in white, or to haue a kingly dignity, and much beauty ſet on them, is not a merit or a reward for the deſert of their works, but of the meere grace and mercie of God for the merits of Chriſt, for whom, we and our works wrought by his Spirit, find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance and fauour, the Law tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that the <hi>reward</hi> is of mercie.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.6</note> And the Goſpell telling vs — <hi>That the ſufferings of this preſent time are
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3362:41"/> not worthy of the glorie which ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> The crowne of life is of Gods promiſe, not of our deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.12.</note> as it is ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation; for when he is tried, he ſhall receiue the crowne of life, which the Lord promiſed to them that loue him.</hi> The things which ſome call merits, (very vnfitly and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the phraſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) are the nurſes of our hope, the prouocations of loue, the ſignes of our election, the forerunners of our future happineſſe, the way of the kingdome, not the cauſe why we reigne. It is Ieſus Chriſt, the holy Lambe of whom it is properly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken:<note place="margin">Reu. 4.11.5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue glorie, and honour, and power:</hi> and, <hi>Worthy is the Lambe that was ſlaine, to receiue power, and riches, and wiſedome, and ſtrength, and honour, and glorie, and bleſſing.</hi> He alone <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed his Church with his owne bloud.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3362:41"/> Our robes are made white in the bloud of the Lambe.</hi> Our perſons,<note place="margin">Reu. 7.14.</note> our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, &amp; our works, haue acceptance with God, onely for Ieſus ſake, as it is ſaid:<note place="margin">Eph. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>He made vs accepted in his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,</hi> and our ſpirituall ſacrifice, <hi>is acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5.</note> As no mans free gift can bind him to giue more, but he that receiues more, is the more bound to him that giues it; therefore hence it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that by the good deeds which God hath enabled vs to do, he is not bound by the debt of his iuſtice to giue vs more, that he ſhould be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt if he gaue it not, but we rather are bound to him. And if he giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reward to our well-doings, this is, not that he is a debtor to the works, but of his owne liberalitie. How vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly are good works ſaid to be meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, ſeeing they are not ours ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally, but Gods?<note place="margin">Phil. 2.13.</note> he <hi>working both the will and the deed,</hi> and that <hi>of his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3362:42"/> owne good pleaſure.</hi> But as they are ours, they are debts due to God by his holy Law binding vs to do them; and more,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note> they are imperfect, <hi>For in many things we offend all,</hi> they are faulty, not done alwaies with ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, fulneſſe of deſire, or not with whole ſtrength, zeale and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as the Lord requireth; yea they are vnequall to the reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence: <hi>When ye ſhall haue done all thoſe things which are commanded you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 17.10</note> 
                  <hi>ſay: We are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants, we haue done that which was our dutie to do.</hi> Let not our hearts be lifted vp in conceit of the worthineſſe of our doings,<note place="margin">Habac. 2.4.</note> as is vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in all Hypocrites; but deſire we that (as they that looke through greene glaſſe, thinke all they ſee greene) the Lord will looke vpon vs in the face of his Annointed, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept vs as righteous in him, <hi>who is our righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 27.24.</note> That as <hi>Iacob</hi> got a bleſſing which was not due to him,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3362:42"/> in the name of his elder brother, and in his clothing: ſo we <hi>putting on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>may be found in him, not hauing our owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt:</hi> and may ſay with the Church (or <hi>ſeede which the Lord hath bleſſed,) I will greatly reioyce in the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa 61.10.</note> 
                  <hi>my ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in my God: for he hath clothed me with the garments of ſaluation, he hath couered me with the robe of righteouſneſſe; as a bridegroome decketh himſelfe with ornaments, and as a bride adorneth her ſelfe with iewels.</hi> Now concerning <hi>faith,</hi> we do not teach, nor beleeue, that we are iuſtified or ſaued for our faith, or the worthineſſe of it: but we cleaue to the word, and beleeue as therein we are taught, namely:<note place="margin">Gal. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>The iuſt ſhall liue by his faith. We are iuſtified by faith, &amp; haue peace with God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.1. Gal. 3.26.</note>—<hi>We are all the children of God, by faith in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3362:43"/> —To him that worketh not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in him that iuſtifieth the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, his faith is</hi> COVNTED <hi>to him for righteouſneſſe.</hi> And that comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table bill of acquittance:<note place="margin">Act. 13.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Be it knowne vnto you, men and brethren, that through this man is preached vnto you forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and from all things, from which ye could not be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the law of Moſes, by him euery one that beleeueth, is iuſtified.</hi> Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand for a fuller cleareneſſe in this point, that like as it is ſaid of <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> continuing in holineſſe and ſound doctrine:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.6</note> — <hi>In doing this thou ſhall ſaue thy ſelfe, and them that heare thee.</hi> It is not meant that <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> or any Miniſter doth <hi>ſaue,</hi> otherwiſe then as inſtruments, <hi>(Who is Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>or who is Apollos, but Miniſters by whom ye beleeued?)</hi> So though no other faith iuſtifieth, but that which worketh by loue, (the ſame neither iuſtifying together with loue, nor
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3362:43"/> faith hauing his efficacie from loue:) yet faith which ſaueth,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>(Ye are ſaued by grace through faith, and not of your ſelues, it is the gift of God,)</hi> ſaueth not as it is a worke, or as it <hi>worketh by loue;</hi> but as it <hi>receiueth</hi> Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.11</note> that in him we may be righteous. Euen as fire giueth comfort to the frozen, and be nummed with cold, not by the light thereof, but by the heate of it. As God giueth his Sonne vnto vs, and in him eternall life: ſo giueth he alſo to euery of his, faith to be as a hand to receiue the gift, ſo that they which <hi>receiue abundance of grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and of the gift of righteouſneſſe, ſhal reigne in life by one, Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> It is true, that true faith, is neuer alone, that is, it is not fruitleſſe, barren or idle, as that in Hypocrites; but it is <hi>effectuall,</hi> or there is a worke of <hi>faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 1.3</note> and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of <hi>loue.</hi> Yet it alone and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grace iuſtifieth, as to them that will be wiſe according to the word,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3362:44"/> it is very manifeſt:<note place="margin">Gal. 2.16.</note> — <hi>Knowing that a man is not iuſtified by the workes of the Law, but by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, euen we haue beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt, that we might be iuſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law; for by the works of the Law, ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified.</hi> This needeth no further declaration, but is as cleare as that ſhort ſpeech of Chriſt to the ſame effect,<note place="margin">Mar. 5.36.</note> 
                  <hi>Onely beleeue.</hi> And that alſo,<note place="margin">Luke 8.50.</note> 
                  <hi>Feare not, beleeue onely, and ſhe ſhall be made whole.</hi> And this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, maintaineth Chriſts honour, and extolleth his bountie, who <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to the thirſtie of the fountaine of the water of life freely.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.6.</note> And it giueth to the broken in heart, and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule much and ſound comfort, in greateſt conflicts and terrors of conſcience, and when for ſinne Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan would draw vs to deſpaire. Let vs then cheare vp our hearts, &amp; refreſh our fainting ſpirits, with the holy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3362:44"/> harmonie of the Apoſtles, all of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſweetly ſounding out this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, of our bleſſedneſſe by faith in Ieſus Chriſt. Saint <hi>Iude</hi> thus exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth:<note place="margin">Iude 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Build vp your ſelues on your moſt holy faith—looking for the mercy of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt vnto eternall life. Iames</hi> requireth <hi>we aske in faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing wauering. Iohn</hi> aſſureth vs, that <hi>it is the commandement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.23</note> 
                  <hi>that we ſhould beleeue on the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. Paul</hi> ſetteth downe very briefly the ſumme of the Goſpell. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 16.31.</note> 
                  <hi>and thou ſhalt be ſaued. Peter</hi> in a great aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly taught,<note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> that <hi>God put no difference betweene them and vs, after that by faith he had purged their hearts. Why tempt ye God to lay a yoke on the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples necks, which neither our fathers, nor we are able to beare? but we beleeue through the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to be ſaued, euen as they do.</hi> Yea <hi>To him giue all the Prophets witneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10.43.</note>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:3362:45"/> 
                  <hi>that through his Name, whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in him ſhall receiue remiſſion of ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>A fourth obiection.</head>
               <p>If good works do not anſwer the righteouſneſſe of Gods Law, nor iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, nor ſatisfie, nor merite before God: it may ſeeme they are vile in your eyes, or at leaſt you make ſmall account of them, and you ſet a doore wide open to carnall liberty, and all licentiouſneſſe of liuing.</p>
               <p>O be it farre from all that profeſſe Chriſtianitie, ſo to thinke or ſpeake; for good <hi>workes</hi> are a maine part of that worſhip of God which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, and will call vs to account for: they are the end of our Election, aſſurances of our Calling, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of our Iuſtification, the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Sanctification, forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Glorification, the effects of grace, the life of Religion, the beauty
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3362:45"/> of Chriſtianitie, witneſſes of faith, nurſes of hope, fruites of loue, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of thankfulneſſe, our ſacrifice to God, our acceptance with men, the difference betweene Saints and reprobates, the truth of repentance, a turning from dead workes, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues from ſcandals, a laſting debt and dutie; they adde honour to our profeſſion, peace to our conſciences, further our reckning; they are ſeales of ſaluation, the way to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, follow vs to Gods tribunall; they are our walking in the waies of God, and our blameleſſe conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without which we are as fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe trees, fitted for the fire, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites that without all helpe ſhall be caſt into hell; for as the word of truth teacheth;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.14</note> 
                  <hi>Without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> Take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge then and be minded, that we beleeue and teach, both a <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of good works, and ſundry excellent
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3362:46"/> 
                  <hi>vſes</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>A <hi>neceſſitie</hi> of good works we do beleeue. Firſt, becauſe of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement:<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt commanded that we ſhould keepe thy precepts dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leu. 19.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy. This is the will of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.3</note> 
                  <hi>euen your ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Secondly, <hi>it is Gods ordination: We are his worma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2 10.</note> 
                  <hi>created in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus vnto good workes, which God hath before ordained, that we ſhould walke in them.</hi> Thirdly, there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the doing, and preſence of good workes, for the manifeſtation of the righteous iudgments of God, when he will come to be <hi>glorified in his Saints,</hi> and crowne his owne works in them:<note place="margin">Mat. 25.35 Reu. 22.12</note> 
                  <hi>For he will iudge all men according to their deeds. And giue to euery man, as his worke ſhall be.</hi> Fourthly, a neceſſity is impoſed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, becauſe we are debters, as it is ſaid:<note place="margin">Luk. 17.10</note> — <hi>We haue done what was our dutie to do.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.12</note> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>Ye are
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3362:46"/> debters, but not to the fleſh, but to God our Creator, Redeemer, and Sanctifier,</hi> Euer thinke we on it,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt gaue himſelfe for vs, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs from all iniquitie, and purifie vs to himſelfe a peculiar people, zealous of good workes.</hi> The obligation and bond of our debt is, our <hi>Baptiſme. —We are buried with him by Baptiſme into death:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that like as Chriſt was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp from the dead by the glorie of the Father, ſo we ſhould walke in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life.</hi> Fiftly, becauſe there is no other <hi>way</hi> to eternall bleſſedneſſe, but by the practiſe of <hi>holineſſe.</hi> For though good workes cannot be the cauſe of ſaluation, but onely Ieſus Chriſt: (as it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I will giue thee for a light of the Gentiles, that thou maiſt be my ſaluation vnto the end of the world:</hi>) yet are they the way and path vnto life and bleſſedneſſe.<note place="margin">Pro. 12.28.</note> 
                  <hi>In the way of righteouſneſſe is life, and in the path thereof there is no death.—Ye
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3362:47"/> haue your fruite in holineſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.22</note> 
                  <hi>and the end, euerlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vſes of good works are many and great, in regard of God, our ſelues, others, and our holy profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>God is glorified</hi> by our good workes, which are (being rightly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) a ſpeciall part of his holy worſhip and ſeruice.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Herein is my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glorified, that ye bring forth much fruite.</hi> His grace is manifeſted by enabling vs vnto a meaſure of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:<note place="margin">Eze. 36.27</note> — <hi>I will put my ſpirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and ye ſhall keepe my iudgements and do them.</hi> God is honoured and praiſed for them, and by them:— <hi>They glorified God for me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 1.23. 1. Pet. 2.9.</note>—<hi>Ye are a peculiar people, that ye ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him which hath called you out of darkneſſe into his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous light.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.11.</note>—<hi>Do it as of the abilitie which God giueth, that God in all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3362:47"/> things may be glorified, through Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> As a father delighteth in a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſonne: ſo God delighteth in all thoſe that beare his image, imitate his holy nature, that take pleaſure in well doing,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.34.</note> whoſe meate and drinke it is to do their fathers will.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by our blameleſſe and good conuerſation, we become fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the example of Chriſt, &amp; of his Saints:<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.15.</note> 
                  <hi>I haue giuen you an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ye ſhould do as I haue done to you. As Chriſt forgaue you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.13</note> 
                  <hi>ſo alſo do ye. Take the Prophets who haue ſpoken in the name of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (of ſuffering affliction, and of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, by our holy life and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, we gaine aſſurance that God hath choſen vs to be heires of ſaluation.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue diligence that ye make your calling and election ſure, for if ye do theſe things ye ſhall neuer fall. —If we loue in deed and truth—We
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3362:48"/> know we are of the truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our hearts before him.</hi> Thus the truth of faith is knowne, <hi>for faith that hath no works is dead,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
                  <hi>being alone. Neither Circumciſion nor vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion auaileth any thing, but faith which worketh by loue.</hi> Thus alſo is the ſoundneſſe of repentance knowne:<note place="margin">Act. 26.20.</note>—<hi>I ſhewed to them, that they ſhould repent, and turne to God, and do works meete for repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, by carefulneſſe of well performing our dutie, we are heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to looke for the performance of Gods free promiſes made vnto vs. So <hi>Moſes</hi> had <hi>reſpect vnto the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the reward.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26</note> 
                  <hi>(Godlineſſe hauing the promiſes of this life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and that which is to come.)</hi> We may looke for, (&amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if God ſee it expedient for vs,) long life, a bleſſed poſterity, peace &amp; plentie, ioy of heart, preſeruation in the euill day, and whatſoeuer good is.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.58.</note> 
                  <hi>Be ye ſtedfaſt, vnmoueable, alwaies
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3362:48"/> abounding in the worke of the Lord, foraſmuch as ye know that your labor is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs not be wearie of well-doing, for in due time we ſhall reape, if we faint not. Know that whatſoeuer good thing any man doth, the ſame he ſhal receiue of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, they that liue righteouſly, eſcape curſes and calamities, when the wrath of God cometh on the children of diſobedience.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>For when God ſpared not the old world: he ſaued Noah the eight perſon, a preacher of righteouſneſſe.</hi> God ſaid he would ſpare <hi>Sodome and Gomorha,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.32. Iſa. 65.14.</note> 
                  <hi>for ten ſake that were righteous. Behold my ſeruants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart: but ye ſhall crie for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houle for vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, they that are of vpright conuerſation, and are ſtudious to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in good workes, ſhall auoid offences: <hi>Giue none offence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.32.</note> 
                  <hi>neither to the Iewes nor to the Gentiles, nor to the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3362:49"/> Church of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18.7. 2. Cor. 6.3.</note> For <hi>wo vnto the world becauſe of offences. Giuing none offence in any thing, that the Miniſterie be not blamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seuenthly, by our good deeds we win others to God, or make way and prepare ſome to conuerſion. <hi>I am made all things to all men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.22</note> 
                  <hi>that I might by all meanes ſaue ſome. Haue your conuerſation honeſt among the Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>that whereas they ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you as euill doers, they may by your good workes which they ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, glorifie God in the day of viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.14.</note> 
                  <hi>I magnifie mine office, if by any meanes I may prouoke to emulation them which are my fleſh, and might ſaue ſome of them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye wiues be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to your husbands, that if any obey not the word, they alſo may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the word be wonne by the conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wiues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eightly, righteous behauiour ſtoppeth the mouthes of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3362:49"/> that they cannot ſpeake ill of vs. So the loyall and iuſt cariage of <hi>Dauid</hi> towards <hi>Saul,</hi> ioyned with loue and meekneſſe, preuailed ſo far that he made this acknowledgment: —<hi>Thou art more iuſt then I.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.17. 1. Pet. 2.15.</note> 
                  <hi>So is the will of God, that with well doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly, by charitable works the poore diſtreſſed are much releeued, and ſuch are commended and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the word of God:<note place="margin">Philem. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>We haue great ioy and conſolation in thy loue, becauſe the bowels of the Saints are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed by thee, brother Iob</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Iob 29.12.</note> 
                  <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered the poore that cryed, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, and him that had none to helpe him; the bleſſing of him that was readie to periſh came vpon me, and I cauſed the widowes heart to ſing for ioy. To do good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.16</note> 
                  <hi>and to communicate for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:3362:50"/>
               <p>Tenthly, when we do ſuch works as beſeeme them that repent, we countenance the Goſpell of Chriſt, and our holy profeſſion. Therefore euen ſeruants are commanded ſo to walke,<note place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>That they may adorne the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God our Sauiour in all things.</hi> And this precept is giuen to all the faithfull:<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> — <hi>Let your conuerſation be ſuch as becometh the Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Furthermore let it be well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that to the wel doing of a good worke, all the foure cauſes muſt meete together: the two externall, the <hi>Efficient</hi> and the <hi>End:</hi> the two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, the <hi>Matter</hi> and the <hi>Forme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the <hi>Efficient</hi> is meant, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>worker,</hi> or <hi>doer</hi> of a good worke, who is no meere naturall man, for he doth not perceiue the things of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14</note> much leſſe do them. No hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, who doth all for himſelfe, euen when he pretendeth moſt holineſſe; as <hi>Iudas</hi> could ſay,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Why was not this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3362:50"/> ointment ſold for three hundred pence, and giuen to the poore? This he ſaid, not that he cared for the poore: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a theefe, and had the bag, and bare that was put therein.</hi> No wicked man,<note place="margin">Pro. 15.8.</note> whoſe very <hi>ſacrifice is abhomination to the Lord.</hi> But he muſt be in Chriſt, a new creature, a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man, one that hath faith <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.9.</note> and which giueth him aſſurance, that for Chriſt, both his perſon and his worke is accepted with God. As God had firſt <hi>reſpect to Abel,</hi> and then <hi>to his offering:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>So it is Gods choſen that he hath ordained to bring forth fruite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and be glorified that they beare much fruite.</hi> He being the true author of all good works, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>in his both the will and the deed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>the End,</hi> and principall ſcope of all our works, is the glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God: <hi>Whether ye eate or drinke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31.</note> 
                  <hi>or whatſoeuer ye do, do all to the glorie of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Honour the Lord with thy ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3362:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:3362:51"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:3362:52"/> and with the firſt fruits of all thine increaſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi> There are alſo other law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubordinate ends of good works, as in thoſe nine ſeuerall vſes before mentioned, is made plaine.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Matter</hi> and ſubſtance of good workes, is not euery deuiſed worke of man vpon his good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and good intent. Our Sauiour reproueth the Phariſies, for their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and ſeruices of God of their owne deuiſing,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> ſaying: <hi>In vaine do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandements of men. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I command you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 12.32</note> 
                  <hi>take heede ye do it; thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, nor take ought therefrom.</hi> So that nothing can be a good worke with God will allow, but onely what he hath commanded. The Law of God tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth what good works we muſt do:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3362:52"/> as Chriſt out of it, anſwered to the yong man, that would know <hi>What good thing he ſhould do,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.16. Phil. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to haue eternall life. Whatſoeuer things are true, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, iuſt, pure, louely, of good report, if there be any vertue, and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny praiſe, thinke on theſe things; theſe things which ye haue learned, receiued, and heard in me, do, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Forme</hi> and manner of doing them muſt be as the Lord commandeth: 1. In faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23. 1. Pet. 2.5.</note> the heart hauing a well grounded perſwaſion, that for Chriſt they are pleaſing to God. 2. In <hi>loue,</hi> as the precept is, <hi>Let all your things be done in loue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.14. Tit. 3.8.</note> Whence ſpringeth, 1. A <hi>carefulneſſe: — They which haue beleeued in God, be carefull to maintaine good workes.</hi> Alſo 2. <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and forwardneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1. Gal. 2.10.</note> — <hi>Be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to euery good worke. Onely they would, that we ſhould remember the poore, the ſame which I alſo was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3362:53"/> to do.</hi> 3. <hi>Timely</hi> for the good of the receiuer.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Withhold not good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thy hands to do it; ſay not to thy neighbour, Go and come againe, and to morrow I will giue thee, when thou haſt it by thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.7.</note> 4. <hi>Chearefully, for God loueth a chearefull giuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>diſcreetly,</hi> and with iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.5.</note> 
                  <hi>For a wiſe mans heart</hi> diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>both time and iudgement.</hi> And as in the <hi>Pſalme:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.5.</note> 
                  <hi>A good man ſheweth fauour, and lendeth and will guide his affaires with diſcretion.</hi> Doing firſt good to <hi>them that excell in vertue,</hi> and then to others, after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Samaritan.</hi> Yea <hi>prouident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> to take occaſions of doing good: <hi>As we haue opportunitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>let vs do good vnto all men, eſpecially to them who are of the houſhold of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Plentifully.</hi> The praiſe of <hi>Tabitha</hi> is,<note place="margin">Act. 9.36.</note> that ſhe was <hi>a woman full of good workes and almes deeds.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3362:53"/> Charge them that be rich,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.18</note> 
                  <hi>that they do good, that they be rich in good workes, readie to diſtribute, willing to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>zealouſly</hi> and earneſtly muſt good workes be done, with feruent deſire of heart, and outward dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. — <hi>He gaue himſelfe for vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>to purifie vs to himſelfe a peculiar people zealous of good workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, <hi>Conſtantly</hi> alſo, and not for twice or thrice, and then giue ouer. <hi>Let vs not be wearie of well doing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>for in due time we ſhall reape if we faint not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we teach good workes, thus we practiſe, thus we encourage all thereto,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.10</note> yea — <hi>We ceaſſe not to pray that we may walke worthy of the Lord, vnto all pleaſing, being fruitfull in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good worke, and increaſing in the knowledge of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="use_and_fruit">
               <head>The ſecond vſe and fruite</head>
               <p>Which we are to make by our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3362:54"/> of holy <hi>Maries</hi> bleſſedneſſe, is, to be informed and taught, that it is the nature of true faith, to apply to our owne ſelues apart, perſonally &amp; particularly, the promiſes of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to <hi>put on Chriſt,</hi> as a man putteth on his owne garment vpon his body: not onely to beleeue that Chriſt and all his riches is <hi>ours,</hi> but alſo that <hi>Chriſt is mine,</hi> and I am his. So ſaid the Spouſe of Chriſt: <hi>My beloued is mine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and I am his:</hi> ſo ſaid the holy mother of Chriſt;<note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſoule reioyceth in God</hi> MY <hi>Sauiour.</hi> It was no affectation of ſingularitie in that gracious woman to ſay, MY <hi>Sauiour,</hi> (as though he had bene hers alone.) But ſo ſhe well expreſſed the life of true and liuely faith vnto vs. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her example, euery Chriſtian for himſelfe is to beleeue his owne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, building his aſſurance, firſt on Gods loue in Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.19</note> 
                  <hi>reconciling vs to himſelfe.</hi> Secondly, and on the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3362:54"/> truth of Gods free and vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble promiſes, ſealed in our hearts by the ſpirit of adoption:— We recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>not the ſpirit of the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.12</note> 
                  <hi>but the ſpirit which is of God, that we might</hi> KNOW <hi>the things that are freely giuen vs of God.</hi> It is a conceit without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty, to think this was a prerogatiue granted to her alone, or to <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> or ſome few that haue it by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation: for euery one that is effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called, doth particularly, with ſuch application to himſelfe, ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue as ſhe did; and hath no ſound and certaine comfort till he ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. Marke it heedfully, how <hi>Paul</hi> ſo applieth to himſelfe the promiſe of life, and then to all, &amp; euery of the faithfull, that loue Chriſts coming: — <hi>I haue kept the faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>henceforth is laid vp for</hi> ME <hi>the crowne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue</hi> ME, <hi>at that day; and not to</hi> ME <hi>onely, but to</hi> ALL <hi>them alſo
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3362:55"/> that loue his appearing.</hi> He that doth not beleeue particularly, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that Chriſt Ieſus is <hi>His</hi> Sauiour, his beleefe is no better then the faith of diuels; they beleeue Chriſt is a Sauiour to ſome men, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not that he is their Sauiour. As of old euery one that ſprinkled his dore poſts with the bloud of the Paſchall Lambe,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.13.</note> was aſſured by the promiſe of God, that he ſhould eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the deſtroying hand of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell: ſo euery one is baptized ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, that he may haue a perſonall beleefe, that <hi>His ſinnes</hi> are waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in Chriſts bloud, and <hi>He</hi> ſhall eſcape the wrath to come. <hi>Philip</hi> will not baptize the Eunuch till he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſuch a faith:<note place="margin">Act. 8.37.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou mayeſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized if thou beleeueſt with all thine heart.</hi> We haue a cloud of witneſſes of the holy ones, that thus apart to themſelues applied the promiſes of God, whoſe ſteps we muſt follow, if
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3362:55"/> we wil haue true peace in our ſoules. <hi>Iob</hi> expreſſeth his faith apartly, and particularly thus:<note place="margin">Iob. 19.25.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> KNOW <hi>that</hi> MY <hi>redeemer liueth.</hi> In <hi>Iſaias</hi> we reade: <hi>My ſoule ſhall be ioyfull in</hi> MY <hi>God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 61.10.</note> In <hi>Abacuk: I will reioyce in the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Abac. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I will ioy in the God of</hi> MY <hi>ſaluation.</hi> In <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie, I will ſay it is my people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhall ſay, the Lord is</hi> MY <hi>God.</hi> So <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is</hi> MY <hi>light and</hi> MY <hi>ſaluation. Elizabeth</hi> the mother of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.43.</note> 
                  <hi>Whence cometh this to me, that the mother of</hi> MY <hi>Lord ſhould come to me? Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle after he was healed of his vnbeleefe, could ſay: MY <hi>God,</hi> MY <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily acknowledgeth: <hi>I liue by the faith in the Sonne of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>who hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> ME, <hi>and giuen himſelfe for</hi> ME. It is no preſumption to beleeue all that God hath promiſed, nor to waite for all he intends to giue vs. But it is the <hi>great ſinne</hi> (for which the holy Ghoſt will reproue the world:) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3362:56"/> they beleeue not on Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.9.</note> As a wounded man hath not comfort of his incarnatiue plaiſter, till it be laid on his ſore: ſo haue we no fruit of Gods ſweete promiſes, till we apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cloſe to our ſoules. Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that the commandements, Thou ſhalt not kil, nor commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, nor ſteale, are giuen to euery of vs? as if he had ſaid, Thou <hi>Iohn, Thomas, Peter, &amp;c.</hi> ſhall obey me when I ſay, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill, &amp;c.</hi> So the promiſes of ſaluation for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, are ſpoken to vs as if he named euery beleeuer ſeuerally. It will do thee no good, nor put any comfort into thy ſoule, to beleeue the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, and life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: except thou beleeue, that thou thy ſelfe ſhalt at the end of the world riſe againe, and enioy life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ias</hi> prophecying of the coming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> into the world,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> ſaith not onely, <hi>A Child is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3362:56"/> borne,</hi> but <hi>vnto</hi> VS <hi>a childe is borne, vnto</hi> VS <hi>a ſonne is giuen.</hi> So the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that were meſſengers of glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, <hi>ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnto</hi> YOV <hi>is borne this day a Sauiour which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi> So the Prophets and Apoſtles lay downe to their hearers their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſinnes, particular puniſhments, and particular comforts when they repent. Our dutie and comfort it ſhall be, where God ſpeaketh to all his generally, to apply it our ſelues particularly. As <hi>Seeke ye my face: my heart anſwered vnto thee, O Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.8.</note> 
                  <hi>I will ſeeke thy face.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="use_and_fruit">
               <head>The third vſe and fruite</head>
               <p>Is comfort and reioycing for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of bleſſedneſſe by faith in Chriſt Ieſus. So the Virgine <hi>Marie</hi> hauing much aſſurance of her owne ſaluation:<note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note> 
                  <hi>Her ſpirit reioyced in God her Sauiour.</hi> So the Lord bad his ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20</note> 
                  <hi>Reioyce that their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3362:57"/> names were writtten in heauen.</hi> Now reioycing which God commandeth, is for good things that are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and not vncertaine. Be it ſo, that ſuch as know not that the Lords loue is towards them, are euer full of doubting and vncertaintie: and ſay, the Apoſtles &amp; Diſciples of Chriſt, by Chriſts reuelation might be ſure and certaine of their owne perſonall and ſeuerall ſaluation, but ſo cannot others. Let ſuch be put in mind, that where true faith is, there is alſo a true aſſurance of bleſſedneſſe: the holy Ghoſt teaching vs, that faith, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and reioycing in the Lord, go together.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtified by faith we haue peace with God, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by whom alſo we haue acceſſe by faith into the grace wherein we ſtand, and</hi> REIOYCE <hi>in hope of the glorie of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4 4.</note> Againe, <hi>Reioyce in the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Agreeable whereto is that in <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.8.</note>— <hi>In whom, though ye now ſee
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3362:57"/> him not, yet beleeuing</hi> YE REIOYCE, <hi>with ioy vnſpeakeable and full of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi> And for aſſurance and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the holy exhortation is:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs draw neare with a true heart in full aſſurance of faith.</hi> We could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this aſſurance of Gods loue, <hi>But that we haue receiued the Spirit which is of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.12</note> 
                  <hi>that we might</hi> KNOW <hi>the things that are freely giuen to vs of God.</hi> He it is that perſwades our hearts infallibly, enabling vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the power, truth, and loue of God to vs.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>We are kept by the power of God, through faith, vnto ſaluation.</hi> What more aſſurance can we deſire? or what ſurer ground of reioycing, then to know that we are kept for ſaluation, and ſaluation kept for vs? as it is there alſo ſaid:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> — <hi>That the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance incorruptible is reſerued in heauen for you.</hi> Yea &amp; that we might haue ſtrong conſolation, we haue <hi>the Lords oath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>abundantly to ſhew to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3362:58"/> the heires of promiſe, the immutabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gods counſell for bleſſing vs.</hi> And as the Lord is true in his promiſes, ſo is he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant in his loue, the word witneſſing that:<note place="margin">Iohn 13.1.</note> — <hi>Hauing loued his owne which were in the world, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them vnto the end.</hi> Hence it is <hi>that we haue boldneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12 Heb. 4.16. Rom. 5.2. 1. Theſ. 1.5</note> 
                  <hi>and acceſſe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence by faith of him.</hi> Knowing the power of the word: <hi>The Goſpell com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto vs in power, and in the holy Ghoſt, and in much aſſurance;</hi> and the power of faith, that it is a ground or confidence,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>A ſubſtance of things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, the euidence of things not ſeene.</hi> The phraſe or ſpeech of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is not to doubt of Gods loue, to weene, trow, or thinke well: but to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence, aſſurance, to beleeue and to know:<note place="margin">Iohn 6.69.</note> 
                  <hi>We beleeue and know that thou art Chriſt, the Sonne of the liuing God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham was ſtrong in faith, fully perſwaded, that what God had promiſed he was able to performe.</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:3362:58"/> Moſt comfortable are the words in <hi>Iohn: Behold what manner of loue the Father hath beſtowed vpon vs, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God. — Now are we the ſonnes of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and it doth not yet appeare, what we ſhall be; but</hi> WE KNOW, <hi>that when he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare we ſhall be like vnto him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is. Paul</hi> vſeth much vehemencie herein:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.5</note> 
                  <hi>Proue your ſelues whether ye be in the faith, examine your ſelues;</hi> KNOW YE <hi>not your owne ſelues, how that Chriſt Ieſus is in you, except ye be reprobates?</hi> And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.16</note> KNOW YE <hi>not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you? Martha</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of her brother <hi>Lazarus</hi> that was dead, ſaith:<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.24.</note> 
                  <hi>I</hi> KNOW <hi>that he ſhall riſe againe, in the reſurrection at the laſt day.</hi> Can we know a certainty of the reſurrection of the dead, and may we not as well know the other parts of our faith which we confeſſe, a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3362:59"/> and true aſſurance of <hi>the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſinnes, and of our liuing euerlaſtingly in the kingdome of Chriſt?</hi> Sure we are, the Lord chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth doubting, and reproueth ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, miſtruſt, fearefulneſſe, vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and wauering, where we haue any promiſe to ſtay vpon.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Let not him that wauereth, thinke that he ſhall receiue any thing of the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 21.21 Mat. 14.3.</note> 
                  <hi>If ye haue faith and doubt not. O thou of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</hi> and <hi>Why are ye fearefull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> 
                  <hi>O ye of little faith?</hi> If it be obiected that very faithfull and holy men haue doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, bene deiected, and bewrayed their lacke of this aſſurance of faith: as <hi>Ionas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionas 2.4.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight. Dauid</hi> when he brake out: <hi>Is his mercie cleane gone for euer?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 77.9.</note> 
                  <hi>doth his promiſe faile for euermore? Iob,</hi> when he ran into extremitie of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.<note place="margin">Iob 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>O that God would deſtroy me, that he would let his hand go, &amp; cut me off!</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:3362:59"/>
               <p>To theſe and the like we returne this anſwer: that like as the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sunne is ſometime eclipſed, and the light of it to vs-ward, is dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for a time: and as <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he had preuailed with God, and got a bleſſing,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.31.</note> yet halted on the one thigh: ſo the holieſt vpon the earth fall; &amp; faile in dutie, and yet recouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues through the ſeed of grace which God hath put in them,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> and ſo conſtantly to the end perſiſt in grace and ſanctimonie.</p>
               <p>Yet to make it plaine by a fuller manifeſtation, know: Firſt, that at the firſt conuerſion of a ſinner, he hath not full aſſurance of Gods loue to him, but beleeuing his ſinnes are pardonable, afterward by ſpirituall growth he cometh to perſwaſion, they are pardoned; laſtly to an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible aſſurance and certainty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as we reade of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 4.21 8.38.</note> and <hi>Paul.</hi> Faith is firſt like a bud, then a
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3362:60"/> bloſſome, and after fruite of a full growth.<note place="margin">Eze. 47.3.</note> As the waters that iſſued out from vnder the Temple, firſt tooke the Prophet to the ancles, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the knees, after to the loynes, laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, became a riuer that could not be paſſed ouer: ſo are the graces of God in his children, ſmall at the firſt, and haue their growth both by degrees, and by attending to the word of his grace.<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.3</note> So <hi>Paul</hi> thanked God <hi>that the faith of the Theſſalonians grew daily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, by ſome fall into a heinous ſinne, faith is much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, euen as a mans body is by a ſharpe and ſore diſeaſe: which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Dauid</hi> to cry,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Caſt me not away from thy preſence, take not thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from me; reſtore to me the ioy of thy ſaluation, and ſtabliſh me with thy free ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, in time of grieuous tentations, when Satans ſuggeſtions moue him to thinke hardly of God,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3362:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:3362:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:3362:61"/> and to thinke of himſelfe that he is but an hypocrite, deceiuing both himſelfe and others; &amp; though God be good to his Saints, yet hath he forſaken him, that he is no true member of Chriſts Church, but as a dead branch. Notwithſtanding this fall in the ſpirituall combate, there is a recouerie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.24.</note> God putting his hand vnder, that though he fall, yet he fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not away. In ſuch fearefull skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes it is with Gods elect, as it was with the Patriarch <hi>Iacob</hi> in his trials, for he once thought, that he had loſt three of his children: <hi>Ioſeph is not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 42.36.</note> 
                  <hi>and Simeon is not, and ye will take Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min:</hi> yet through the kindneſſe of his God he receiued them all three a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to the great ioy and gladneſſe of his heart. So when faith ſeemeth to be quite loſt and extinguiſhed, or at the moſt, like a ſparkle of fire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with embers, yet where it once was in truth, it is recouered fully, (as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3362:62"/> in <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi>) and manifeſteth it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.25.</note> ſomewhile, in 1. <hi>Prayer;</hi> for though fainting faith ſaid, <hi>We periſh:</hi> yet ſtrugling, and recouering faith <hi>cryed:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionas 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord ſaue vs. Ionas</hi> ſoule fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in him, Yet <hi>remembred the Lord, and his prayer came to him in his holy Temple.</hi> Otherwiſe, by 2. <hi>Hope: — On thee O Lord do I waite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.15.</note> 
                  <hi>thou wilt heare me my Lord my God. Why art thou caſt downe my ſoule, why art thou diſquieted within me? Waite on God, for I will yet giue him thankes, he is my preſent helpe and my God.</hi> In 3. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation alſo:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.26.</note> 
                  <hi>If he ſay I haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thee, behold here am I, let him do to me as ſeemeth good in his eies.</hi> The perplexitie of ſome in ſundrie temptations is not vnlike <hi>Dauids,</hi> and his men at Ziglag, who in their owne ſenſe were miſerable, when their wiues and children, (and all that they had) were caried a way cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues; and yet behold, after carefull
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3362:62"/> vſing of good and diſcreete meanes,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 30.3.19.</note> recouered all that the <hi>Amalekites</hi> had taken away. So though for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we are deiected, and ſeeme to be forlorne: yet God in his time,<note place="margin">Pſal. 63.5.</note> (which is alwaies ſimply beſt) giueth a recouery, with comfort and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the Lord. <hi>Noahs</hi> arke may be much toſſed, rocked and ſhaken; but drowned it cannot be: ſo the faith of the Saints is aſſaulted, weakened, and battered, but neuer finally and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouercome.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>We are troubled on euery ſide, yet not diſtreſſed: perplexed, but not in deſpaire; perſecuted, but not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken; caſt downe, but not destroyed. The buſh burned and conſumed not,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note> for God was in the middeſt of it.</p>
               <p>To draw to an end, that the <hi>called, choſen,</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> may haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere reſt, tranquillitie, comfort of mind and conſcience, a true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted aſſurance of eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe by Ieſus Chriſt, God that is
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3362:63"/> the giuer of the gift, giueth alſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods Spirit beareth witneſſe with our ſpirit, that we are the children of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.24.</note> And as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith (who moſt clearely and often tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth this infallible certainty,) <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we know he abideth in vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4.13.5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>euen by the Spirit which he hath giuen vs.</hi> Now the fruits of our ſpirit renewed by his Spirit, though they are not all, in all beleeuers, in like meaſure, and at all times; yet are they of ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, as giue vs comfort, and diſcerne vs from the vngodly and wicked, they are to vs pledges of Gods loue, and as the gate of heauen: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a ſearching out of our ſinnes and defections, a groning vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of them, an hatred and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them, a ſtriuing againſt them, a labour and watchfulneſſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent ſinnes, and timely to cut off the occaſions of them; a mourning for the ſinnes of the land, an hungring
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3362:63"/> after righteouſneſſe, true loue to God and his children, and the word of his grace; patient hope, waiting on God, knowing that he will bleſſe both proſperitie and aduerſitie vnto vs; a deſire aboue all things to pleaſe God, vprightneſſe of heart without hypocriſie, and endeuour to keepe a good conſcience, to walke in our calling faithfully and chearefully; boldneſſe with God, in humble prayer, thankfulneſſe for all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to vs, theſe and the like do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure vs that we are borne of God. As for our certainty to perſeuere in grace, the foundation of it is not on the earth, (for ſo it would fall,) but on the Lords faithfulneſſe. He now hath the keeping of vs, and of our bliſſe; it is not in our hands, as it was in <hi>Adams,</hi> who quickly loſt it. <hi>He will confirme you to the end,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that ye may be blameleſſe in the day of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. God is faithfull, by whom ye
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3362:64"/> are called vnto the fellowſhip of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Yea he hath made a ſure Couenant, ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new vs,<note place="margin">Iere. 32.40.</note> that <hi>He will put his feare in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, that we may neuer depart from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Maruellous is the light that God hath put into mans eye, whereby he ſeeth the earth about him, and the heauens aboue him, without paine, in a moment: but more admirable is the ſight of faith, which can ſee before the world God electing vs to ſaluation in his Sonne our head, in the world redeeming vs by his Sonne our <hi>Mediator,</hi> after the world glorifying vs with his Sonne our King in the heauens for euermore. The loue of God (which is our life) is ancient, free, ſweete, conſtant, great, vnſpeakable, incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and eternall. God hath giuen his Sonne to be our Sauiour: his Spirit to be our Comforter,<note place="margin">Iſa. 60.19.</note> and he will be
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3362:64"/> our glorie eternally. Let all the Lords redeemed ſay, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, with deuout and religious hearts: <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit reioyceth in God my Sauiour. Bleſſing and glorie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 7.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and wiſedome, and thankſgiuing, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and power, and might, be vnto our God for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:3362:65"/>
            <head>The comfort of a Chriſtian, by aſſurance of Gods loue to him.</head>
            <l>MY peace of heart, my happineſſe,</l>
            <l>My ſweeteſt ioy is this:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 1.4.</note>That God me lou'd, ere world was made,</l>
            <l>And purpos'd me to bliſſe.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 13.1.</note>This ſure decree for laſting life,</l>
            <l>This bountie great and free:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 1.5. Iohn 6.39. Rom. 5.12.17.</note>He hath fulfild in Chriſt his Sonne,</l>
            <l>Whom he hath giuen for me.</l>
            <l>Our fall in Adam fearefull was;</l>
            <l>We left a curſed race:</l>
            <l>Yet Chriſt our King, the Lord of life,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.11. Iohn 5.25.</note>Hath ſau'd vs, by his grace.</l>
            <l>A powerfull voice his Gospell hath,</l>
            <l>To raiſe vp dead in ſinne:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.14. Act. 11.17.</note>Whom he doth call effectually,</l>
            <l>Are ſtrongly brought to him.</l>
            <l>I call'd, I come: I runne with ioy,</l>
            <l>I haſte Lord vnto thee:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 10.49</note>As <hi>Bartimeus</hi> boldly went,</l>
            <l>When Chriſt ſaid: Come to me.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Act. 11.18.</note>Repentance thou doeſt giue to life,</l>
            <l>The ſeale of thy ſure loue:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 21.32.</note>By it I ſtand in ſtate of grace,</l>
            <l>As new-borne from aboue.</l>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:3362:65"/>
            <l>When Law doth giue me ſight of ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7. 1. Chro. 34.27.</note>
            </l>
            <l>My ſoule doth melt and rent:</l>
            <l>My troubled ſp'rite, and broken heart,</l>
            <l>Doth grieue and much lament.<note place="margin">Iob 33.27. Ier. 31.19. Pſal. 32.5. 1. Tim. 1.13</note>
            </l>
            <l>I am aſham'd of all my faults,</l>
            <l>To God I them confeſſe:</l>
            <l>I iudge my ſelfe a wickedwretch,</l>
            <l>And of my ſelfe helpleſſe.</l>
            <l>When ſinne and Satan bid deſpaire,</l>
            <l>Gods voice ſpeakes to mine eare:</l>
            <l>Beleeue in Chriſt, his grace is great,<note place="margin">Act. 16.31.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Shake off miſtruſtfull feare.</l>
            <l>He mercie ſhewes to humbled men,</l>
            <l>Heart-wounded he doth cure:<note place="margin">Luk. 4.18. Luke 1.53.</note>
            </l>
            <l>He fils the fainting ſoule with ioy,</l>
            <l>Their comfort he makes ſure.</l>
            <l>He great, he good, he ſlow to wrath,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.6.</note>
            </l>
            <l>He kindneſſe ſhewes to all:</l>
            <l>He caſts-off none that ſeeke to him,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.37.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Yea he doth ſinners call.</l>
            <l>All ye that wearie are of ſinne,</l>
            <l>Whom it doth lode and quell:</l>
            <l>Come ye to me, I will you eaſe,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note>
            </l>
            <l>My peace with you ſhall dwell.</l>
            <l>Theſe gracious words of Chriſt my Lord,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2. Ier. 31.3.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Theſe comforts ſtrongly pierce:</l>
            <l>This Gospell moues my heart to bleed,</l>
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:3362:66"/>
            <l>My ſobs for ſinne increaſe:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note>That I my God, my Father deare,</l>
            <l>With ſinnes ſhould ſo prouoke:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39.9.</note>And hauing found ſuch mercy rare,</l>
            <l>Should ſo caſt off his yoke.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9.1.</note>A floud of teares I do deſire,</l>
            <l>To weepe both night and day:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.30.</note>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I haue grieu'd the ſpirit of grace,</l>
            <l>And turn'd his face away.</l>
            <l>In ſtead thereof, ſome holy flames,</l>
            <l>Are kindl'd from aboue:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Luke 7.47.</note>And many ſinnes to me forgiuen,</l>
            <l>My God I do much loue.</l>
            <l>My ſelfe, my ſeruice ioyfully,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.106.</note>A freſh to him I vow:</l>
            <l>With ſetl'd heart, to tread the path,</l>
            <l>That he doth beſt allow.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 5.22.</note>My care is now to walke with God,</l>
            <l>To truſt in him for aye:</l>
            <l>On him to hope, and him to loue,</l>
            <l>In all things to obey.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31. Pſal. 145.2. Pſal. 16.3.</note>His glorie I will ſoundly ſeeke,</l>
            <l>His praiſes forth will tell:</l>
            <l>In Saints on earth will I delight,</l>
            <l>In vertue that excell.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.111.</note>His holy word will I eſteeme,</l>
            <l>As rule of life moſt pure:</l>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:3362:66"/>
            <l>And ſtriue to liue as it directs,</l>
            <l>To make my calling ſure.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note>
            </l>
            <l>The life of grace, as way to bliſſe,</l>
            <l>I wholly will embrace:</l>
            <l>And ſhun allwaies of wickedneſſe,</l>
            <l>That may my life diſgrace.</l>
            <l>Yea I will warre againſt all ſinne,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.12 Ephe. 6.10.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And ſtoutly ſtill will fight:</l>
            <l>Perſwaded ſure through Chriſt my King,</l>
            <l>To conquer by his might.</l>
            <l>And though through frailtie of my fleſh,</l>
            <l>I faile, I fall, or ſinne:</l>
            <l>Mine inward man doth it deteſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note>
            </l>
            <l>And loath to lie therein.</l>
            <l>My heart can witneſſe, that by me</l>
            <l>When Gods Law was tranſgreſt:</l>
            <l>It was not I, but Adam old,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.17.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Indwelling-ſinne, my gueſt.</l>
            <l>Which like vnto Goliah ſtrong,</l>
            <l>Doth daily vexe and rage:</l>
            <l>Whereas mine inward man is weake,</l>
            <l>Like Dauid yong of age.</l>
            <l>Yet ſhall mine inward Dauid once,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.51.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Triumphantly preuaile:</l>
            <l>And great Goliah ouerthrow,</l>
            <l>Who doth ſo ſore aſſaile.</l>
            <l>Meane while, each conqueſt ouer ſinne,</l>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:3362:67"/>
            <l>Makes Gods loue to appeare:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.17</note>And I new thankes, and praiſe to him,</l>
            <l>Will offer in his feare.</l>
            <l>Another ſigne of Gods ſure loue,</l>
            <l>I cannot chuſe but know:</l>
            <l>In that both Diuell, and foes did rage,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 41.11.</note>Yet could not me downe throw.</l>
            <l>For God my ſtrength, did me vphold,</l>
            <l>And kept me ſafe and ſure:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.22. Pſal. 136.1.</note>He is no changling now to ſhrinke,</l>
            <l>His mercies ſtill endure.</l>
            <l>And though my fals bring griefe and feare,</l>
            <l>I ſhall not fall away:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.28.</note>The ſheepe of God cannot be loſt,</l>
            <l>Although they go aſtray.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 34.11.</note>For Chriſt doth go to wilderneſſe,</l>
            <l>When one ſheepe he doth lacke:</l>
            <l>He ſeekes it there, vntill he find,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.12.</note>And brings it on his backe.</l>
            <l>The Couenant old to do vs good,</l>
            <l>And put in vs his feare:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note>That we from him ſhould not depart,</l>
            <l>It doth my ſoule much cheare.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22.32</note>That Peters faith might neuer faile,</l>
            <l>Chriſt here on earth did pray:</l>
            <l>He now in heauen my Aduocate,</l>
            <l>Will me vphold and ſtay.</l>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:3362:67"/>
            <l>A ſurer ſeale, a ſweeter pledge,</l>
            <l>God giues me inwardly:</l>
            <l>His holy Spirit, which in my heart,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Doth Abba Father crie.</l>
            <l>My free Adoption he makes knowne,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.20</note>
            </l>
            <l>My deare Redemption ſeales:</l>
            <l>My full Attonement with my God,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note>
            </l>
            <l>He inwardly reueales.</l>
            <l>He bends my heart vnto his will,<note place="margin">Eze. 36.27</note>
            </l>
            <l>He guides me by his Law:</l>
            <l>To truſt in him, to loue him ſtill,</l>
            <l>On him to ſtand in awe.</l>
            <l>His pow'r ſometimes though I feele not,</l>
            <l>Through ſinne, and fleſhly feare:</l>
            <l>Yet ſeede of grace, ſowne in my heart,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.9.</note>
            </l>
            <l>In time doth me vpreare.</l>
            <l>His loue ſo old, ſo ſweete, ſo firme,</l>
            <l>My heart with ioy doth fill:</l>
            <l>Whom once he loues, he neuer leaues,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.1.</note>
            </l>
            <l>But doth embrace him ſtill.</l>
            <l>The legacie of laſting life,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note>
            </l>
            <l>His gift it is, moſt free:</l>
            <l>How then can any thing debarre,</l>
            <l>Or keepe the ſame from me?</l>
            <l>Wherefore were ſeales to Couenant ſet?<note place="margin">Mat. 26.28 Iſa. 34.9.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Why did our Lord oft ſweare?</l>
            <l>But to cheare vp the fainting ſoule,</l>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:3362:68"/>
            <l>And make his loue appeare.</l>
            <l>Hence I by faith, vnto my ſelfe</l>
            <l>Gods promiſes apply:</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note>And ſay with Paul, Chriſt ſo lou'd me,</l>
            <l>That he did for me die.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 18.17. Ioh. 20.24. Mat. 12.20.</note>And though with Peter I fall farre,</l>
            <l>Or do with Thomas doubt:</l>
            <l>Thou that breakſt not the bruiſed reede,</l>
            <l>Nor ſmoking flaxe put out:</l>
            <l>As thou didſt them reſtore in grace,</l>
            <l>And made them to abide:</l>
            <l>So wilt thou me, who onely art</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 20, 28.</note>My King, my God, my guide.</l>
            <l>So whether it be thy holy will,</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.8</note>That I ſhall liue or die:</l>
            <l>I am thine owne, and ſo ſhall be,</l>
            <l>Now and eternally.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.47.</note>Wherefore in God my Sauiour,</l>
            <l>My ſoule do thou reioyce:</l>
            <l>In prayſing of his holy Name,</l>
            <l>Lift vp a chearefull voice.</l>
            <l>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.22</note>In offering vp ſuch ſacrifice,</l>
            <l>Lord make me ſpend my daies:</l>
            <l>Make it my ſtudie, and my ioy,</l>
            <l>To giue thee thankes and praiſe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_dialogue">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:3362:68"/>
            <head>The Complaints of a Sinner. The Comforts of our Sauiour.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>COnceiu'd in ſin,</hi> in ſin brought forth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5. Rom. 7.14 Rom. 5.12. Gen. 8.21.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Sold vnder ſinne I was:</l>
               <l>Seede of all ſinne, in me: vile, vaine,</l>
               <l>I vglie am, alas.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>A Sauiour I, am to that flocke,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.17 Ioh. 1.13. 1. Cor. 6.11</note>
               </l>
               <l>Whom I anew create:</l>
               <l>Thou borne of God, by new-birth art,</l>
               <l>Through me, in happie ſtate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Law of God,</hi> as iuſt, and good,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.10.7.12.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Doth bleſſe who it fulfill:</l>
               <l>But me for my foule faults and ſinnes,</l>
               <l>It doth both curſe and kill.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>The holy Law of God moſt high,</l>
               <l>I haue fulfilled for thee:<note place="margin">Rom. 10.4 Heb. 8.10. Act. 16.31.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Beleeue the Couenant of my grace,</l>
               <l>And bleſſed thou ſhalt be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>The guilt of ſinne,</hi> breeds griefe, &amp; dread,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.21 7.11.</note>
               </l>
               <l>It woundeth as a ſword:</l>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:3362:69"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38.</note>An hell on earth it ſeemes to me,</l>
               <l>What helpe for this O Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.18 1. Pet. 2.24.</note>When I the iuſt, for vniuſt died,</l>
               <l>And bare your ſinnes on tree:</l>
               <l>From guilt of ſinne, I clearly ſet</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Eze. 18.27.</note>Repentant ſinners free,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23. 1. Cor. 10.5.</note>
                  <hi>Sharpe puniſhments,</hi> with wrathfull rods,</l>
               <l>By each ſinne we procure:</l>
               <l>What mortall man can them eſcape,</l>
               <l>Or yet the ſtripes endure?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.29. Ioh. 3.16. Deut. 8.2.</note>The Lambe of God your ſinnes hath borne,</l>
               <l>Beleeuers are made free:</l>
               <l>To worke amendment, rods are ſent,</l>
               <l>To trie, and humble thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7.23</note>
                  <hi>Sinnes bondage,</hi> blinds, beſots my mind,</l>
               <l>My heart to euill bends:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note>To hate the good, to loue the bad,</l>
               <l>To aime at ſinfull ends.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.22.</note>Thou ſeruant made to righteouſneſſe,</l>
               <l>By my grace art ſet free:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.4</note>Though yet a while thou tug and toile,</l>
               <l>Till warfare ended be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:3362:69"/>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>Through <hi>fleſh ſo fraile</hi> I oft am foild,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What I would not, I do:</l>
               <l>What good I would, I leaue vndone,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note>
               </l>
               <l>This weakeneſſe works my wo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>Yet ſpirit oft the fleſh doth courbe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.22. 1. Cor. 9.27 Rom. 8.13</note>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhall in time all ſway:</l>
               <l>This battell will a conqueſt bring,</l>
               <l>To perfect peace make way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>wicked world</hi> on euill ſet,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.14.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Allures me vnto ſinne:</l>
               <l>Hath ſundry ſnares, and fearefull plagues,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>And oft wraps me therein.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>Thy home is heauen, ſeeke after it;<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aine worldly pleaſures flie:</l>
               <l>A friend to world, is foe to God;<note place="margin">Iam. 4.4.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Loue thou the things on hie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>vglie Diuell</hi> ſweld with ſpite,<note place="margin">Reu. 12.17.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To ſinne doth tempt me ſtill:</l>
               <l>And Lion-like ſeekes here and there,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Whom to deuoure and kill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:3362:70"/>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.7. Ioh. 12.31.</note>By faith reſiſt, and he will flie,</l>
               <l>From heauen he is out caſt:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note>And vnder foote he ſhall be trod,</l>
               <l>Through my great power at laſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2.15.</note>
                  <hi>Vnwelcome death,</hi> ſo gaſtly grim,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntimely comes with ſpeed:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note>My precious life it will cut off,</l>
               <l>And keepes me in much dreed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55. Philip. 1.21</note>I conquer'd Death, Deaths ſting is gone,</l>
               <l>It ends thy cares and ſinne:</l>
               <l>To laſting life its as a gate,</l>
               <l>By it thou entreſt in.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 16.24.</note>
                  <hi>Hell-torments</hi> are a liuing death,</l>
               <l>The paines of eaſeleſſe wo:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</note>For ſinners theſe prepar'd of old,</l>
               <l>Theſe fright my heart alſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 42.6.</note>Mourne for thy ſinnes, abhorre thy ſelfe;</l>
               <l>Haue ſtedfaſt faith in me:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 20.14.</note>I vanquiſh'd death, and hell alſo,</l>
               <l>For all that faithfull be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:3362:70"/>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <l>The dreadfull <hi>day of doome</hi> drawes on,</l>
               <l>When all men muſt appeare:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10</note>
               </l>
               <l>The Iudge is iuſt, our ſinnes are great,<note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note>
               </l>
               <l>What will then eaſe my feare?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAVIOVR.</speaker>
               <l>The righteous Iudge thy Sauiour is,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.27.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Who will thee ſurely bliſſe:</l>
               <l>But hypocrites will ſend to hell,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.51.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The righteous doome is this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SINNER.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O Sauiour ſweete, my life, my light,</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct me to <hi>know</hi> thee:</l>
                  <l>What is thy will, what is that good,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt laid vp for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfained <hi>faith</hi> in me increaſe,</l>
                  <l>And make me ſtrong therein:</l>
                  <l>To vanquiſh Satan, doubts, and feares,</l>
                  <l>And each preſumptuous ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Teach me with patient <hi>hope,</hi> to waite</l>
                  <l>On thy good pleaſure ſtill:</l>
                  <l>With true ſubmiſſion of my heart,</l>
                  <l>And conqueſt of my will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:3362:71"/>
                  <l>My frozen heart ſet thou on fire,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>loue</hi> of thee my Lord:</l>
                  <l>With loue of grace, of heauen, of Saints,</l>
                  <l>With loue of thy ſweet word.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The holy <hi>feare</hi> of thy great Name,</l>
                  <l>So put into my heart:</l>
                  <l>As may cauſe me from wickedneſſe,</l>
                  <l>And from all ſinne depart.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſacrifice of daily <hi>thankes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From ground of heart I giue:</l>
                  <l>To thee my God, with ioyfulneſſe,</l>
                  <l>By whom my ſoule doth liue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let all my life ſet forth thy praiſe,</l>
                  <l>And therein neuer ceaſſe:</l>
                  <l>O grant me growth in godlineſſe,</l>
                  <l>O let mine end be peace.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3362:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3362:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3362:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3362:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3362:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3362:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3362:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3362:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3362:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3362:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3362:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3362:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3362:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3362:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:3362:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:3362:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:3362:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3362:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3362:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3362:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3362:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3362:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3362:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3362:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3362:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
